<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rash oaths unwarrantable: and the breaking of them as inexcusable. Or, A discourse, shewing, that the two Houses of Parliament had little ground to make those oaths they have made, or lesse ground to take, or presse the taking of them, being it is easie to be apprehended, they never intended to keep them, but onely made them for snares, and cloaks for knavery, as it is clearly evinced by their constant arbitrary and tyranicall practices, no justice nor right being to be found amongst them; by meanes of which they have declaratorily, and visibly lost the very soule and essence of true magistracy, (which is, the doing of justice, judgement, equity ... In which is also a true and just declaration of the unspeakable evill of the delay of justice, and the extraordinary sufferings of Lievtenant Colonell John Lilburne, very much occasioned by M. Henry Martins unfriendly and unjust dealing with him, in not making his report to the House. All which with divers other things of very high concernment, are declared in the following discourse, being an epistle, / written by Lievtenant-Colonell John Lilburne, prerogative prisoner in the Tower of London, to Colonell Henry Marten, a member of the House of Commons of England ... May 1647.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E393_39</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201615</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862115</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114264</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114264)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E393[39])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rash oaths unwarrantable: and the breaking of them as inexcusable. Or, A discourse, shewing, that the two Houses of Parliament had little ground to make those oaths they have made, or lesse ground to take, or presse the taking of them, being it is easie to be apprehended, they never intended to keep them, but onely made them for snares, and cloaks for knavery, as it is clearly evinced by their constant arbitrary and tyranicall practices, no justice nor right being to be found amongst them; by meanes of which they have declaratorily, and visibly lost the very soule and essence of true magistracy, (which is, the doing of justice, judgement, equity ... In which is also a true and just declaration of the unspeakable evill of the delay of justice, and the extraordinary sufferings of Lievtenant Colonell John Lilburne, very much occasioned by M. Henry Martins unfriendly and unjust dealing with him, in not making his report to the House. All which with divers other things of very high concernment, are declared in the following discourse, being an epistle, / written by Lievtenant-Colonell John Lilburne, prerogative prisoner in the Tower of London, to Colonell Henry Marten, a member of the House of Commons of England ... May 1647.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 25 1647".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marten, Henry, 1602-1680 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114264:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114264:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Raſh Oaths unwarrantable: And the breaking of them as
inexcuſable. Or, A DISCOURSE, ſhewing, that the two Houſes of Parliament
had little ground to make thoſe Oaths they have made, or leſſe ground to
take, or preſſe the taking of them, being it is eaſie to be apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
they never intended to keep them, but onely made them for ſnares, and cloaks
for knavery, as is clearly evinced by their conſtant arbitrary and
tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call practices, no juſtice nor right being to be found amongſt
them; by meanes of which they have declaratorily, and viſibly loſt the very
ſoule and eſſence of true Magiſtracy, (which is, <hi>the doing of
juſtice, judgment, equity and right</hi>) and are become a dead carkaſſe.
In which is alſo a true and juſt DECLARATION of the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able evill of
the delay of juſtice, and the extraordinary ſufferings of Lievtenant
Colonell <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> very much occaſioned by M. <hi>Henry
Martins</hi> unfriendly and unjuſt dealing with him, in not making his Report
to the Houſe. All which with divers other things of very high concernment,
are declared in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, being an Epiſtle written by
Lievtenant-Colonell <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> Prerogative-priſoner in the Tower
of <hi>London,</hi> to Colonell <hi>Henry Marten,</hi> a Member of the Houſe
of Commons, and Chaire-man to the Committee for conſideration of the
Liberties of the <hi>Commons of England.</hi> May 1647.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 5.2.4.</bibl> 
               <p>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to
utter any thing before God; but when thou voweſt a vow unto God, deferre not
to pay it: for he hath no pleaſure in fooles: pay that which thou haſt
vowed</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Numb. 30.2.</bibl> 
               <p>If a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an vow a vow
unto the Lord, or ſweare an oath to hind his ſoule with a bond, hee ſhall
not breake his word, he ſhall do according to all that proceedeth out of his
mouth.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. 23.21.</bibl> 
               <p>VVhen thou ſhalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt
not ſlack to pay it: for the Lord thy God will ſurely require it of thee,
and it will be ſin to thee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 4.2.</bibl> 
               <p>And thou ſhalt ſweare the Lord liveth, in truth, in judgment,
and in righteouſneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ezek. 17.15,16,19.</bibl> 
               <p>Shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he break the
Covenant, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd be delivered? As I
live, ſaith the Lord God, ſurely in the place where the king dwelleth that
made him king, whoſe oath he deſpiſed, and whoſe covenant he brake,
even with him in the midd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of
Babylon he ſhall die; and my covenant that he hath broken, even it will I
recompence upon his own head.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſ. 4.2,3.</bibl> 
               <p>By ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aling, and committing adultery, they
breake out, and bloud toucheth bloud; therefore ſhall the land mourn.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ier. 6.19.</bibl> 
               <p>Heare O earth, behold I will bring evill upon this people, even
the fruit of their thoughts, becauſe they have not harkened to my words, nor
to my law, but rejected it.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <p>SIR, When Iſrael degenerated from the Law of her Soveraigne Lord
and King, and followed her own crooked wayes, the Lord himſelf, as one that
was<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114264:2"/>not delighted in her deſtruction, but rather with her
preſervation, cries out again her, to make her aſhamed of the evill of her
wayes. <hi>How is the faithfull city b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>come a harlot? it was full of judgement, righteouſneſſe
lodged in it, but now murd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ers.
Thy ſilver is became droſſe, thy wine mixt with water. Thy Princes are
rebellio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and companions of
theeves: every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judge not the fatherleſſe, neither
doth the cauſe of the widdow come unto them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Lord, the
Lord of hoſts, the mighty one of Iſrael, ah, I will eaſe me of my
adverſaries, and avenge me of my enemies, Iſa.</hi> 1.21,22,23,24.</p>
            <p>Sir, an enemy to you he is not, that ſhall cordially and
heartily tell you of your faults, with a deſire to reclaim you from the evill
of your wayes by ſo doing, <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 141.5. which task though unpleaſant in it ſelfe, he that
never in his life knew ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to
flatter, nor play the hypocrite and diſsembler, is urgently neceſſitated
now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his own preſervation, to
undertake.</p>
            <p>And therefore Sir, to give you your due and right, I muſt
ingenuouſly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> knowledge, that I
have for a long time looked upon you, as one of the great p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Liberties of the Commons
of <hi>England,</hi> and your name amongſt all ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and unbiaſsed men, hath been
extraordinary famous this preſent Parliament there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and for this you
ſuffered an expulſion of the Houſe, and a reproachfull a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> unjuſt impriſonment in the Tower
of <hi>London,</hi> by the guilded men of the time who (you then diſcovered)
carried two faces under one hood; &amp; many monet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> (if not ſome yeares) you continued an ejected
perſon from your juſt place in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Houſe: And ſince your re-admiſſion again, have there in
your Speeches behave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your ſelfe
ſo gallantly for your Countrey, that your name and fame hath loud been
ſpread abroad by it: Yea give me leave to tell you, that one of your own
Members eſteemed very honeſt, but by me too prudentiall; that is to ſay,
too cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly, and too much for himſelfe and his ſelfiſh intereſt, in a
time when a No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern tempeſt was
likely to ariſe, told me in the Tower, that the true lovers
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Countrey in
<hi>England</hi> were more beholden unto M. <hi>Henry Marten</hi> for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſincerity, uprightneſse,
boldneſse and gallantry, then to halfe, if not all tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that are called conſcientious men in the Houſe.
And truly Sir, having had th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
happineſse (for ſo I eſteemed it) often to be in your company, I have
admire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe gallant
diſcourſes for the Liberty of this Nation that have flowed from yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo that when I firſt made my appeale to the Houſe
of Commons the 16. of June 1646. and heard that my buſineſse was referred
to a Committee where M. <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> had the Chaire, I was not a little refreſhed, being
even where I would hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſhed
and deſired to be; thinking that you, of all the men in the Houſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Commons, would have been the
moſt ſenſible of me and my condition: But muſt deale truly with you, I
found it otherwiſe: For after, by the earneſt ſoll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> citation of my wife and friends, you and the Committee
had examined my bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114264:2"/>and paſſed (as I was informed) gallant and excellent
Votes upon it; but yet you (by your negligence and delay, if not
wilfulneſſe) exaſperated the ſpirits of the Houſe of Lords againſt
me, and expoſed me to their mercileſſe fury and devouring indignation, by
delaying my Report: And truly Sir, I muſt give this commendation of them,
<hi>That the tender mercies of the Houſe of Lords are cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> For,
upon your examining my buſineſſe, and not reporting it, they tooke
courage to themſelves, and lock'd me up moſt illegally, barbarouſly and
tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally in New gate above three weeks cloſe priſoner, from the
ſociety of my wife, children, or friends; and would neither ſuffer me to
receive either meat, drink, money, nor any other neceſſaries, from the
hands of my wife, maid, or friends; nor ſuffer my wife to come into the
Priſon-yard to ſpeake with me before my Keepers out of my window; the
ſtory of which you may more fully read in the 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30.
pages of my late printed Book called <hi>Londons Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie in chaines
diſcovered;</hi> and in my <hi>Speech before your ſelfe</hi> (at the
Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee) now in print, and called <hi>An Anatomie of the Lords
tyrannie,</hi> pag. 3, 4, 5, 6. and in the ſecond Edition of the <hi>Outcries
of oppreſſed Commons,</hi> pag. 21, 22, 23. All this while my wife and
friends following you day by day, with all the importunity in the world, to beg
and intreat of you to make my Report, for want of which I was likely to be
deſtroyed by the devouring Houſe of Lords; but you would not do it: ſo
that in ſome ſenſe I may complaine with <hi>Iob</hi> (in reference to
you, and the reſt of my timorous friends in the Houſe) <hi>My kinsfolke
have failed me, my familiar friends have forgotten me, and mine acquaintance
are verily eſtranged from me, Job</hi> 19.13,14. which did hearten the
tyrannicall Houſe of Lords, further to go on with their cruelty and tyrannie
towards me; and then upon the 11. of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 1646. at their Barre, paſt a
moſt lawleſſe, illegall, and unjuſt ſentence againſt me, <hi>To pay
foure thouſand pound to the King, to be ſeven yeares a priſoner in the
Tower of London, and for ever to be uncapable to beare any Office or Place in
milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or in civill government, in Church or Commonwealth,</hi> as more at
large you may read in the Sentence it ſelfe, printed in the 30, 31, 32, 33,
34. pages of a little book called <hi>Vox Plebis:</hi> and what illegall
cruelty and tyrannie I have ſince ſuffered and indured in my impriſonment
in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> even to the hazzard of my life and being, and
the deſtruction of my wife and helpleſſe children, you may largely read
in ſeverall printed Books; as <hi>Liberty vindicated againſt Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
pag. 16, 17, 18, 19, 22, 23. <hi>Londons Liberty in chaines diſcovered,</hi>
pag. 31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>Regall tyranny diſcovered,</hi> pag. 1, 47, 48, 49,
62, 63, to 78. but eſpecially in my late Epiſtle to Col. <hi>Weſt</hi>
the Lievtenant of the Tower, called, <hi>The oppreſſed mans oppreſſions
declared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after the fore-mentioned Sentence, being committed to the
Tower, there to be kept onely in ſafe cuſtody for ſeven yeares, as by the
Warrant you<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114264:3"/>may read printed in <hi>Vox Plebis, pag.</hi> 34,
35. I was by the Lievtenant thereof with out ground or cauſe, moſt
illegally divorced from the ſociety of my wife, fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> by himſelfe, who afterwards obtained by his owne
ſolicitation, an Order for his indemnity from the Lords, the ſeverity of
which by him was executed upon me for above eleven weeks together, as by the
fore-mentioned Books you may ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand, and when by my wives
Petition, and my owne, both of which yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may read in the 65, 66, 67. 68, 69, 71, 72. pages of my Book
called, <hi>Londons Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in chaines,</hi> I had obtained the juſt
priviledge to be heard before a Committe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appointed by the Houſe of Commons on purpoſe, where you your
ſelfe again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (to my then great
refreſhment) was in the Chaire, before whom I had two hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings upon two
ſeverall dayes, and I muſt ingenuouſly confeſſe, I had as faire
an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> juſt play before you, as any
man in England could deſire, having free liberty, with out interruption, to
ſpeake whatſoever I in my owne underſtanding, conceive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might be for my benefit and advantage,
to your praiſe and honor, in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of your well doing I deſire
to ſpeake it, and my laſt diſcourſe then with you and the Committee,
was ſo abundantly ſatisfactorie and well pleaſing unto you that your
ſelves by ſpeciall order the 6. Novem. 1646. commanded me to brin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it in unto you in writing, upon the 9.
of Novem. next, which I accordingly did and ſince printed it, not doubting
then but within fourteen daies after, I ſhould have been a freeman, freely
ſet at libertie as unjuſtly impriſoned, and againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good and knowne Law of England, for as
high as this, if not higher, I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
been informed was the reſult of the Committee then, and the temper of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Houſe towards juſtice a thouſand
times better then now it is.</p>
            <p>Sir, I muſt confeſſe, I deſired you then upon ſome
weighty reaſons which gave you, to forbeare the Report foure or five daies,
but when I ſee that thing fell not out according to my expectation, I ſent
immediately to you with al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
earneſtneſſe ſpeedily to make my Report, and you gave thoſe I ſent
to you very faire words, which truly I muſt tell you, would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the bellies of me, my wife nor
children, nor procure us money to buy bread to doe it; whereupon having high
thoughts of your honeſty, and your gallant integrity to the love of the
Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Commons of England, grounded (as I conceived) upon a good
foundation, and backed with high and reſolved reſolutions, I did not onely
with all the honourable reſpect I could, ſend my wife unto you, to
beſeech and intreat you, to be ſenſible of my trying condition, and to
doe me and all the Commons of England (who were and are not a little concerned
in me) that juſtice and right, as without further delay to make my Report to
the Houſe for me, but I alſo ſent unto ſeverall of my friends in the
Houſe and City, in the moſt candideſt manner I could, that I knew had a
familiar acquaintance with you, earneſtly preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to improve all
their intereſt in you, to get you to make my Report,<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114264:3"/>and
when I could not prevaile with you that way, I writ a few importuning lines to
you, and the like to others of my friends, which I knew were dear unto you, and
when that would not doe, I ſent ſome of your owne Countrey-men unto you,
whoſe Commiſſioner and repreſenter you are, to improve their utmoſt
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in you, and I alſo gave you a gentle touch or two in print of my
great ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering by your neglect. Sir, in ſhort, wanted I a wife, I
ſhould not I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of it, uſe ſo much wooing to the faireſt and
vertueſt woman in England, though with a rich portion in Lands and money, to
obtaine her for my wife, as I have done to you to make my Report, having (I
proteſt it before the preſence of God) left no juſt meanes (and others
though I periſh, I will never take) unat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, that all the wits and
braines I have could think of, to obtaine this peece of reaſonable juſtice
at your hands to make my Report for me to the Houſe, which you are bound in
duty, conſcience, juſtice and honour to doe for mee long ſince, without
one tenth part of that importunate ſolicitation, that I for the greateſt
part of a yeare together have uſed to you.</p>
            <p>Sir, I pray remember the 29. Chap. of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which
requires you not only to doe impartiall juſtice, but ſpeedie juſtice
without delay: the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge though at laſt he did juſtice, yet he
is called the unrighteous Judge becauſe he would not do it ſpeedily, but
ſuffered the poor widdow to pump and importune him for it; but ſay I to
you, I wiſh my Judges were not worſe then the unrighteous Judge.</p>
            <p>But Sir, ſeeing it is to no purpoſe, I can no longer now
forbeare, but muſt write you my mind to the purpoſe, coſt it what it
will, being now at preſent as careleſſe of you, as you are and have been
of me, and my long (but I will not ſay unſupportable) ſufferings, though
I might truly ſay it, if it were not that I had a full, faithfull, and
ſoule-ſatisfying God, to reſt and rely upon, and the diſtreſſes and
hardly to be undergone portion of my wife and little infants: But Sir, I
beſeech you, give me leave, before I lanſh into the deep, a little mildly
to expoſtulate with you, in a friendly way before we fall out, and to demand
this queſtion of you, what I have ſaid or done to you, to give you any
tolerable cauſe to deale thus with me, as you have done, as by your delay of
your duty to deſtroy me, and given me too juſt cauſe in reference to you,
to ſay with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 55.12,13,14. <hi>For it was not an enemy
that reproached me, then I could have borne it: neither was it he that hated
me, that did magnifie himſelf againſt me, then I would have hid my ſelf
from him; but it was thou, ah man, mine equall, my guide, and mine acqaintance,
we took ſweet counſell together:</hi> And truly Sir, the evill doings of a
friend are the moſt piercing and wounding, and the leaſt to be indured, and
the moſt odious to God, and deteſtable amongſt all rationall and gallant
men, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.4. to the 9. Ch. 12.6. and Ch. 20.10,11,12. But Sir, if
you have nothing to lay to my charge in reference to your ſelf, I deſire to
know if you have any thing to accuſe me of in reference to the 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114264:4"/>publike, have I deerted my intereſt? or betraid the
Liberties of my fellow Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England? or have I been ſluggiſh,
ſlothfull, or cowardly in mannaging the buſineſſe I have in hand? or
have I been impatient in my ſufferings, &amp; by my mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and folly
deſtroyed my buſineſs? or given grounded advantage to my adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries?
If all or anie of theſe can be juſtly laid to my charge, I deſire not to
be ſpared.</p>
            <p>But Sir, if you can ſay nothing againſt me by way of
miſcarriage to you in particular, or the publike in generall, then I pray you
give me leave to demand of you this queſtion, What have you to ſay for your
ſelfe, that you have thus delayed to make my report, and thereby over and
over, againe and againe have hazzarded my deſtruction and utter ruine,
contrary to law, honeſty, juſtice, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and conſcience?</p>
            <p>If you ſhould ſay, it is not ſeaſonable, <hi>and that the
temper of your Houſe is ſuch that to make it, it would do me nor the
Kingdome no good, but rather a miſchief, in haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding the confirmation of
the Lords tyranny towards me by a vote of your Houſe, whoſe ſpirits are
extreamly exaſperated againſt me above all men in England.</hi> To
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which, what do you elſe then hereby give me too juſt cauſe to
ſay of your Houſe, in which ſo many that profeſſe honeſty ſit,
though it bee but little demonſtrative by their actions, that you are a
corrupted and degenerated generation of men, that are fallen from doing of
Juſtice to the executing of Tyranny, and from maintaining, defending, and
protecting (according to your duty, and the end of your ſitting where you do)
the Lawes and Liberties of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> to the betraying,
ſubverting and deſtroying them, and ſo have all of you forfeited your
truſt, and your Parliamentary power, which (as you your ſelves ſay, 1.
par. Book Decl. p. 150.) <hi>was given you to provide for the Peoples weales,
but not for their woes, and have thereby abſolutely abſolved and
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged the people from all ſubjection to you, and given them cauſe
that ſent you, to call you home, and chuſe honeſter men in your places,
to call you to a ſtrict accompt for all your tyranny, oppreſſion and
trechercy, and know what you have done with all their money;</hi> which they
may juſtly (by your own arguments againſt the King) do: See the ſecond
Edition of the <hi>Outcries of oppreſſed Commons,</hi> p. 4, 5, 6, 7, 14,
15, 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>And in caſe of diſobedience from you to your truſters, and
impowers the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Shires, Countreyes, and Corporations that chooſe
you, what do you elſe, then thereby give them cauſe to look upon you, as
you have this foure or five years looked upon the King, and deale by you, as
you have dealt with the King, even to wage war againſt you, for betrayers of
your truſt, which they and the whole Kingdome repoſed in you, who are now
degenerated from a juſt Houſe of Parliament (the end of calling <hi>of
which by the Law, is to redreſſe miſchiefs and grievances that daily
happen,</hi> 36. <hi>E.</hi> 3.10. but not to augment and wholly increaſe
them) into a conſpiracy and conſederacy of lawleſſe, unlimited, and
unbounded<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114264:4"/>men, that have actually deſtroyed the Lawes and
Liberties of England, and that will have no rule to walke by but their owne
corrupted and bloody wills, and thereby have ſet up the higheſt Tyranny
that can be ſet up in the world, againſt which, by your owne principles,
the Kingdome may juſtly riſe up in Armes as one man, and deſtroy all the
fore-ſaid conſpirators without mercy or compaſſion, <hi>as a company of
devouring Lions, ravening Wolves, and crafty Foxes,</hi> that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
the poore flocks of lambs, and ſheep of this diſtreſſed Kingdome, the
peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Inhabitants thereof; for take away Law (as the Parliament in a
tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent meaſure hath done) and deny us juſtice and right, as is
conſtantly in a great meaſure done unto us by the Parliament: And what are
we now better then the brute beaſts of the field? the weakeſt of which are
torne in pieces, devoured, and deſtroyed by the ſtrongeſt, for
remedie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which the Parliament againſt
the King took up Armes, and when they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d no Law of the Kingdome to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them in ſo doing, they make
uſe of the law of nature and reaſon, and tell the King, <hi>Book Dec.</hi>
1 <hi>part pag.</hi> 207.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this Law is as old as the Kingdome, that the Kingdome
muſt not be without a meanes to preſerve it ſelfe;</hi> but in which of
our Statutes this is writ, I never yet could heare, ſee, nor read of, and am
very ſure it is no where but in their own Declarations, and ingraven in the
heart of man as a principle of nature and reaſon, which as they very well and
juſtly ſay, <hi>teacheth a man</hi> or <hi>Kingdome to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve its
ſelfe,</hi> 1 <hi>part Book Dec. pag.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. 93, 94. 112, 123. 202. 465.
466. 726, 728. ſee 2. Edition <hi>of the Outcries, pag.</hi> 12, 13.</p>
            <p>And if this Doctrine be true, as you avouch it is, then it will
much more ſerve againſt your ſelves then the King, becauſe the King is
ſo fenced about with the Lawes of the Kingdome, that it is impoſſible for
a man or Magiſtrate to bee more, and if you are but a betruſted power,
impowered <hi>protempore,</hi> by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for no other end in the world,
<hi>but to provide for their weale and happineſſe, and to redreſſe
their miſchiefs and grievances</hi> unfortified at all, by the
eſtabliſhed knowne and declared Law of the Kingdome, degenerate from your
truſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Liberties, and trades, overthrow their Lawes, and the
Bounds that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> and tyrannize over their
perſons ten times worſe then ever the King did, or his wicked and evill
Miniſters of Juſtice, the Judges and Paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee Monopolizers, eſpecially
all of whom you cannot deny but he at the beginning of your Seſſion
ſurrendred up to you to be puniſhed by you according to Law &amp;
Juſtice, which in them you extreamely perverted and tooke bribes, for the
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting the capitalleſt of them, and otherwiſe made uſe of them to do
more miſchiefe ſince to the Common-wealth then ever they had done before,
by aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any thing for Law that you would propound to them, by meanes
of which you with your wicked and unbounded Priviledges, have dared to
exerciſe the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteſt<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114264:5"/>and grandeſt tyranny over the
lives, liberties, trades, properties, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Freemen of England,
that ever was, I dare poſitively aver it, ſince it was a Nation, governed
by an eſtabliſhed and declared Law, <hi>to your eternall and everlaſting
ſhame I ſpeake it:</hi> ſo that truly, if the Freemen of England
ſeriouſly look upon all your late publike, and to us viſible actions, and
compare them with their former enjoyments, they may juſtly take up
<hi>Miach's</hi> lamentation and ſay with him to you, <hi>The good man is
periſhed out of the earth, and there is none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right amongſt you men: they
(or you) all lie in waite for blood: they (or you) hunt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man his brother
with a net: that they, or you, may do evill with both hands ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, the
Prince asketh and the Judge asketh for a reward, and the great man he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth
his miſchievous deſire, ſo they wrap it up,</hi> (therefore woe unto the
Parliament, for) <hi>the beſt of them is as a briar, the moſt upright is
ſharper then a thorne hedge, the day of thy watchmen, and thy viſitation
cometh,</hi> now (with a vengeance) <hi>ſhall bee their perplexity;</hi>
therefore, O all ye underſtanding Commons of England, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to your
Parliament Truſtees, <hi>truſt ye not in a friend, put ye no confidence in
a guide, for your enemies are the men of your owne Houſe, Micah</hi>
7.2,3,4,5,6.</p>
            <p>Therefore M. <hi>Martin,</hi> I profeſſe it before you, and
all the world, that were I rationally able, I would make no ſcruple of
conſcience to help forward with my ſword in my hand, the diſtruction of
every lawleſſe, tyrannicall, treacherous man amongſt you, that I ſhould
groundedly know to be a ring-leader in the fore-ſaid tranſcendent
vileneſſe, then I ſhould to help to deſtroy ſo many rats or devouring
vermin; and by your owne fore-mentioned Principles, Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
Proteſtations, Oathes, Actions and doings, it will undeniably be juſtified
to be lawfull for all the Commons of Englands to do the ſame towards you.</p>
            <p>But now Sir, let us come to ſome particulars, in the firſt
place the 29. <hi>Chap, and the moſt excellent Petition of right,</hi> which
I call the Engliſh-mans legall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, doth clearly condemne all the
pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes amongſt you, for
<hi>they expreſſely ſay, that no Freeman ſhall be taken and
impriſoned, or be diſſeized of his freehold or liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or
free-cuſtomes, or be out-lawed, or exiled or any otherwiſe deſtroyed, nor
we will not paſſe upon him nor condemne him, but by lawfull judgement of
his Peers,</hi> (that is to ſay equalls, or men of his owne condition) <hi>or
by the Law of the Land. We will ſell to no man, we will not deny or defer to
any man either iuſtice or right, and that no man be impriſoned without
cauſe ſhewed, or expreſſed in his Warrant of Commitment, nor no man
refuſed</hi> Habeas Corpus's <hi>for any cauſe whatever, nor no man taken
by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, nor ſuggeſtion made to our Lord the King, nor his Counſell,
unleſſe it be by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment or Preſentment of his good and lawfull
People of the ſame neighbourhood where ſuch deeds be done,</hi> (25. E.
3.4.) <hi>in due manner, or by Proceſſe made by Writ O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall at the
common Law;</hi> nor <hi>that none be put out of his Franchiſes, nor of
hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Free-holds, unleſſe he be
duly brought in to anſwer, and fore-judged of the ſame by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:114264:5"/>courſe of the
Law,</hi> and that no man <hi>hereafter be compelled to make or yeeld any
guift, bond, benevolence, taxe, or ſuch like charge, without common</hi>
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> Now compare your daily and
hourly actions to thoſe good, juſt, and unrepealed Laws, and bluſh for
ſhame.</p>
            <p>But to wipe all this off, you will it may be ſay the ſame,
that is ſaid in your Declaration of the 17 of Aprill 1645, Booke Decl. 2 part
pag. 879. <hi>That the end of the Primitive institution of all government, is
the ſafty and weale of the people, which is above all Lawes, and therefore
the Kingdome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imbroyled in warre, neceſſitated, naceſſitie
compells you to doe many actions contrary to the knowne Lawes of the Land,
without the doing of which actions, wanting the puntillo of the Kings
conſent, you could not ſave your ſelves, nor the kingdome,</hi> will
admit all this for a truth, I pray then why doe you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch illegall,
devilſh, impoſſible to be kept, contradicting Oaths, and Covenants, upon
all the Freemen of <hi>England?</hi> upon ſuch ſever penalties that all men
muſt be disfranchiſed or deſtroyed that will not take them, and in them
without any <hi>proviſoes, eautions, limitations, or declared exceptions, and
reſervation,</hi> tye them to maintaine the Law of the Land, and the
<hi>lawful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rightes and</hi>
liberties of the <hi>Subjects of</hi> England, is not this to force men to
ſweare to contradict and oppoſe to the death all your actions, and to
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory you for doing thoſe actions, becauſe they are contrary to the
Law, and Liberties of England? O yee, forſworne men, for ſo I may call you
all, that have taken theſe illegall, damnable, helliſh, and ſoule
inſnaring Oaths, becauſe ye do your ſelves, and ſuffer to be done
daily, ſuch things as tends to the abſolute diſtruction of the Lawes, and
the lawfull Liberties of the freemen of England, which by all theſe Oaths you
have ſworne to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and defend, with all your might, and yet there is
not one juſt, nor righteous man amongſt you, that dare avowedly and
publiquely, to the whole Kingdom proteſt againſt all the reſt, but by
parſilent patient and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſtant ſeting there owne approve of all their
actions: O ye unworthy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne men in the higheſt degree, for this may
too juſtly be the ſtile, and title of all, and every one of you without
exceptions, in the condition of the viſableſt beſt of whom, for Millions
of Gold I would not be, for if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, ſwearings, and falſe ſwearings
be ſo odious, abominable, and deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto God as in Scripture he
declares they are, read <hi>Exod</hi> 20.7. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.11.12
<hi>Num.</hi> 30.2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.21.22.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4.
<hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.4.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.13.14.15.16.17.18.19. <hi>Jer.</hi>
24.10, <hi>Zek.</hi> 5.3.4.9.8.16.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then woe, wee, and vengance upon earth is your vadoubted
portion, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> everlaſting woe,
and indignation in the world to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114264:6"/>But that I may not be ſentenced for raſhnes
in ſaying this which is not in your Oath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and Covenants, I will ſite your owne words, and
leave them to your judgement to paſſe ſentence upon them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in your Proteſtation of the 5 of May 1641, I find you
ſweare in theſe words, <hi>To maintaine and defend the lawfull Rights and
Liberties of the Subject, and every perſon that maketh this Proteſtation,
in whatſoever he ſhall doe in the lawfull purſuance of the
ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſecondly, in your Vow and Covenant, which you commanded to
be taken througho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the whole
Kingdome, <hi>You vow in the preſence of Almighty God the Searcher of all
hearts that you doe in your Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that the forces raiſed by
the two Houſes of Parliament, are raiſed and continue for their juſt
defence, and for the defence of the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> (which
what that is I thinke never a one of your ſelves knowes,) <hi>And Lawes and
Liberties of the Subject, against the Forces raiſed by the King and a little
below you all that tooke that Oath, declare, vow, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to
aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t all perſons that
ſhall take this Oath, in what they ſhall doe in purſuance thereof</hi>
and if ſo, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aver it for a
truth, that all the men of <hi>England</hi> that have taken this Oath, are
bound to aſſiſt me, or any other whatſoever that ſhall oppoſe the
Lords and Commons ſitting at <hi>VVest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> for their apparant
indeavoring the diſtruction of the Liberties of the Subject.</p>
            <p>And in the third place, in the preamble to the League and
Covenant, fram'd in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and moſt baſely, illegally, and
unjuſtly, obtruded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>England,</hi> and the Freemen thereof, with an
unſupportable penalty, I find that amongſt the things, the Fraimers of it
had before their eyes, this is one, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The true publique Liberty, ſafety and Peace of the Kingdome,
wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ones private condition is included,</hi> And in the third
Article of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, you and all thoſe that took it, <hi>ſweare
ſencerely,</hi> really, <hi>and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in your ſeverall e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ditions, to endeavour with your estates
and lives, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to preſerue the Rights and Privileges of the Parliament;
and the lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdome, and I am ſure the Parliament hath often
declared</hi> (though in action; they have viſablely denied it) <hi>that they
have no Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges for the deſtruction of the Kingdome, but for the
preſervation of it,</hi> nor no Privileges for the over-throwing of good and
wholſome Lawes, <hi>but<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114264:6"/>for the defending and preſeruing
of them,</hi> nor no Privileges for the tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling under their feet the
Liberties of the Kingdome, <hi>but to maintaine them in their luſter and
glory,</hi> and what they are, you may in part read be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and in your owne
Declaration.</p>
            <p>Firſt part <hi>booke Decl.</hi> page 6. 7. 38. 39. 77. 123. 201.
202. 209. 277. 278. 458. 459. 548. 660. 720. 845. ſee the ſecond edition
<hi>of the out-cryes of oppreſſed Commons.</hi> page 8.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give you but one notable inſtance, of the moſt
rememberable Vengence of God upon the <hi>Hungarians</hi> for breaking and
violating their Faith and Covenant, made with the <hi>Turke,</hi> and it is in
the Turkiſh Hiſtory made of the Life of <hi>Amurath the ſecond, the
ſixt King of the</hi> Turkes: In which Hiſtory the <hi>fourth edition,
printed by</hi> Adam Iſlip, 1631, <hi>I read that the</hi> Hungarians,
<hi>were much diſtreſſed by inrods and ſpoyles made by the ſaid</hi>
Amurath, <hi>whereupon the States and great men of</hi> Hungary
<hi>chuſed</hi> Vladiſlaus <hi>King of</hi> Polonia, <hi>for their King,
and Captaine Generall, and he made that, famous man</hi> Huniades <hi>his
Generall in</hi> Tranſliluania, <hi>who obtained ſeverall moſt notable
Victories againſt the</hi> Turkes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>as you may read in the foreſaid
Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> folio 267. 269. 273. 277. one of which is extraordinary
remarkable; that <hi>Huniades</hi> with 15000.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought a pitcht-field with about
80000. <hi>Turkes and after five houres there fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a feirce and bloody fight, totally overthrew the</hi>
Turkes <hi>by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aine dint of
ſword,</hi> and juſt about that time <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and
wonder of his age for gallant achevements, revolted from the <hi>Turke,</hi>
which with his great loſſes be the valiant <hi>Hungarians,</hi> ſo te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>fied old <hi>Amurath,</hi> that in a
very great feare of himſelfe and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he made a peace,</hi> (to his owne particuler great
loſſe,) <hi>for ten yeares with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>gar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the capulations whereof were,</hi> Firſt,
<hi>that</hi> Amurath <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw all his forces and garriſons, ſhould
clearely depart out of</hi> Seruia, <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ſame unto the
p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſeſſion of</hi> George
<hi>the late Diſpot, the right</hi> Lord <hi>and</hi> Owner <hi>thereof.</hi>
(then in armes and confideracy with the <hi>Hungarians</hi>) <hi>Delivering
alſo freely unto him his two ſonnes</hi> Stephen <hi>and</hi> George,
<hi>who was bereft of their ſight, he had long time keept in ſtraite
priſon.</hi> Alſo, <hi>that from henceforth he ſhould make no claime unto
the Kingdome of</hi> Moldavia, <hi>nor to that part of</hi> Bulgaria, <hi>which
he had in the late Warres loſt,</hi> And finally, <hi>that he ſhould not
invate nor molest the</hi> Hungarians, <hi>nor any part of the kingdome, during
the whole time of that peace, and to</hi> paie 40000. <hi>Duckats for the
Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of</hi> Carambey <hi>one of his Generalls, which conditions by
ſolome</hi> Oath were confirmed, Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, <hi>Vlad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aus</hi>
taking his Oath upon the Holy Evangle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s, and <hi>Amurath</hi> (by his Ambaſſoders) upon their
Turkiſh Alcoron, <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114264:7"/>inviolable to obſerve the ten yeares
peace, <hi>and</hi> Amurath <hi>forthwith faith fully performed thoſe things
that he was preſently to doe,</hi> follo 292. <hi>but by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadtion
of divers Princes, but eſpecially of</hi> Iulian <hi>the</hi> Cardinall,
<hi>the</hi> Popes Legat, <hi>who in his large and ſet ſpeech in a full
convention, urged that againſt a perfidious enemie,</hi> (as the Turke was)
<hi>it is lawfull for a man to uſe all cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, force and deceit, deluding
craft with craft, and fraud with fraud, and ſaith he, by craft the</hi> Turke
<hi>firſt paſſed into</hi> Europe, <hi>and by little and little he crept
into that Kingdome, and never kept faith with any. It is ſometimes law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
for the common-weale ſake, neither to ſtand to our Leauges, neither to
keepe our faith with them that be themſelves faithleſſe; lawfull ſaith
he it is to breake unlawfull Oaths, eſpecially ſuch as are thought to be
against right reaſon, and equitie, therefore</hi> ſaith he <hi>make no
conſcince of the League you made with the</hi> Infidell, <hi>upon which the
King</hi> Vladiſlaus condeſcended to be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Cardinall, from
his Oath and Covenant, and prepaires for wars againſt the Turkes, and the
Turke with his army met him, and pitched battle within Arvarna, that fatall
place to the Hungarians, and when the battle came cloſe to be joyned, it was
cleare of the Chriſtians ſides, who had put to flight both the wings of the
Turkiſh armie, <hi>inſomuch that</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th <hi>diſmayed with the flight of his Souldiers, was about to
have fled himſelfe cut of the maine battle, had he not bin ſtayed by a
common ſouldier, who lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hands upon the raines of his bridle ſtayed him
by force, and ſharply reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for cowardize:</hi> And <hi>Amurath</hi>
ſeeing the great ſlaughter of his men, and all brought into extreame
danger, beholding the picture of the crucifix in the diſplayed enſignes of
the voluntarie Chriſtians, pluckt the writing out of his boſome, wherein
the League was compriſed, and holding it up in his hand with his eyes caſt
up to Heaven, ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold thou crucified</hi> Chriſt, <hi>this is the</hi>
League <hi>thy</hi> Chriſtians <hi>in thy name made with me, which they have
without cauſe violared. Now if thou be a God, as they ſay thou art, and as
we dreame, revenge the wrong now done unto thy Name, and me, and ſhew thy
power upon thy perjurious people, who in their deeds deny thee their God.</hi>
Whereupon there began a moſt cruell and feirce fight, the ſucceſſe of
which within alittle <hi>while wholy fell to the</hi> Turkes, <hi>who having
ſlaine King</hi> Vladiſlaus, <hi>and diſcomforted his Army,</hi> Huniades
<hi>that moſt valiant Captaine was forced to fly for his life, and it is
obſervable, that in this battle were deſtroyed all the chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe Authors and Actours</hi>
(<hi>yea</hi> Iulian <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi>) <hi>in breaking the Oath, Covenant,
and League, they had made with the</hi> Turke, <hi>Folio</hi> 297. 298. which
overthrow proved a fatall and diſmall blow to the Hungarians, which may be a
good warning to all men in the world,<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114264:7"/>not raſhly to enter
into an Oath or Covenant, but delibrately, and with a reſolved reſolution
enviolably to keepe and obſerve it, which is impoſſible for any man
breathing to do yours.</p>
            <p>For firſt I read in the 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> Chapter 1 that all and
every Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, and all and every other Eccleſiaſticall
Perſon, and other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Officer, and Miniſter, of what
eſtate, dignity preheminence, or degree, ſoever he or thay be, or ſhall
be, and all and every temporall Judge, Juſtice, Mayor, and other lay or
temporall Officer, and Miniſter, and every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon having your
highneſſe ſees or wagges within this Realme, or any your Highneſſe
Dominions &amp;c. ſhall take that Oath following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>THat the King is the onely ſupreme Governour of this Realme, and
of all other his Highneſſe Dominions and Countries, as well in all
Spirituall or Eccleſiaſticall things or cauſes, as Temporall.</q>
            <p>And a little below all that takes it (which all you Parliament
men) muſt and ought to doe, or elſe you cannot ſit, as by the Statute of
the 5 <hi>Elz.</hi> 1. appeares, ſweares and promiſes, that from henceforth
<hi>I ſhall beare faith and true Alleagence to the Kings Highneſſe, his
Heires, and lawfull Succeſſors, and to my power ſhall aſſiſt and
defend all juriſdictions, priviledges, preheman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, and authorities,
granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſſe, his Heires, and
Succeſſors, vnited and annexed to the imperiall Crowne of this
Realme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by the Oath of Allegiance inacted the 3 of <hi>Jam.</hi>
chapter 4. which principally and originally was made for Popiſh Recuſants
to take and for ſuch men of England as traviled beyond the Seas to ſerve
any Forraigne State, or Prince, though of late yeares as I am informed,
impoſed upon all Members of Parliament before they are admitted to ſit
there, in which Oath, you and every one that takes it, <hi>ſweares and
declares in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God and the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that our
Soveraigne Lord King</hi> Charles <hi>is lawfull and rightfull King of this
Realme, and of all other his Majeſties Dominions and Countries, and that
the</hi> Pope, <hi>neither of himſelfe, nor by any Authority of the Church on
Sea of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, <hi>or by any
other<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114264:8"/>meanes with any other,</hi> (marke the laſt clauſe
well) <hi>hath any power or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to deſpoſe the King, or to
diſpoſe any of his Majesties kingdomes or dom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mious, or to authoriſe any
Forraigne Prince to invade or annoy him, or his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, or to give
liſceuce or leave to any of them to beare Armes, raiſe Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, or to
offer any violence or hurt to his Majesties Royall Perſon, State, or
Government, or to any of his Majeſties Subjects within his
Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a little below, he that takes that Oath ſweares, <hi>I will
beare Faith and true Allegiance to his Majestie, his Heires, and
Succeſſors, and him, and them will, defend to the uttermost of my power,
against all conſpiracies and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts whatſoever,</hi> (marke the word
whatſeover) <hi>which ſhall be made against his or their Perſons, their
Crowne and Dignitie, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence or
Declaration, or otherwiſe,</hi> (make the word otherwiſe well,) <hi>and
will doe to my best endeavour to diſcloſe or make knowne unto his
Majeſty, his Heires, and Succeſſors, all treaſons and treacherous
conſpiricies, which I ſhall know or heare of, to be against him or
them,</hi> And below the Oath ſaith, <hi>I do beleeve, and in conſcience am
reſolucd, that neither the</hi> Pope, <hi>nor any perſon whatſoever,</hi>
(note the foure laſt words well) <hi>hath power to abſolue me of this Oath,
nor any part thereof, which I acknowledge by good and full autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to be
lawfully miniſtred unto me, and doe renounce all Pardons and
Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations to the contrary, and all theſe things I do plainly &amp;
ſincerely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſweare, according to theſe expreſſe words
by me ſpoken according to the plaine and common ſence, and understanding of
the ſame words, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny equevocation, or menthall evation, or ſecret
reſeruati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, whatſoever: And I
doe make this recogniction and acknowledgemeni heartily, willingly and
truly,</hi> upon the true faith of a Chriſtian. <hi>So helpe me God,</hi> And
adde unto theſe your fore-mentioned Covenants, and upon them all I conclude
it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any man breathing to keepe them.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, ſet aſide the evill ingredients of theſe two Legall
or Statute Oaths fore-mentioned, which were eaſie in my judgement to be
evinſed, eſpecially that clauſe of the Oath of Supreamicy, recorded 1
<hi>Eliz.</hi> 1 the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words of which are, <hi>That the</hi> King
<hi>is the onely Supreme Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of this Realme, and of all other his
Highneſſe Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as well in all Spirituall or
Eccleſiaſtiall things or cauſes, as Tempor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay nothing of the Temporal part of it, I will deſire you
to ſatisfie me in two or three things of the Spirituall.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether or no Jeſus Chriſt, by God the Father was not
appointed<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114264:8"/>to be the perfect Law-maker, and Law-giver, unto
his viſible Church on earth under the Goſpell? and ſo to ſettle it,
that there ſhould be no roome at all left for Kings, Parliaments, or any
other power on earth to adde to, or detract from what he by the eternally and
everlaſting aſſigament of his Father was to doe in that particuler?</p>
            <p>Secondly, whether or no he hath beene faithfull in executing fully
the will of his Father in this particuler?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, whether or no, to deny his faithfulneſſe, or to ſet
up in the Spirituall Church, Houſe, or City of Jeſus Chriſt; the dictats,
lawes, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juntions, or commands of Kings, Parliaments, or any other earthly
power whatſoever be not an abſolut denyall of the faithfulneſſe of
Jeſus Chriſt, a calling the Scripturea lie, and falſe thing and a
Declaration that he that we owne of our annointed Meſias or Seviour is a
Theeſe Deluder, and falſe Prophet, and not the true reall and great
Prophet, profeſſed of old to be ſent into the world, as the Atoner of man
unto God, the King of Saints, as well as the King of Kings, unto whom all power
in Heaven and Earth was to be committed, to make abſolute, perfect,
ſperituall Lawes. unalterable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable, by any King, Parliament, or
Potentats whatſoever?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, whether there can be greater treaſon committed on
earth, by man againſt Jeſus Chriſt, then to diſclaime and renounce him
and his abſolut Kingſhip? by ſwearing that either the Pope, or any King,
Parliament, or Potentats, are the head, or onely ſupreame Governour in their
ſeverall Kingdomes Dominions, or Juriſdictions, in all Sperituall or
Eccleſiaſticall things or cauſes?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, whether Kings, Parliaments, and Mageſtraites, as
Kings, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Mageſtrates, have any thing at all to doe with the
Sperituall Houſe, City, or Church of Chriſt on earth? and whether that if
any of them clame any intereſt, power, or authority, in the Church of
Chriſt, it be not by vertue of their Saintſhip? not Kingſhip, and whether
or no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice
of the ſoule, ſpirit, or inward renewed man, be not the abſolute alone
and onely right of God? and as much his ſingle due with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compettitors, as
the obedience and ſubjection of the body, outward man, and eſtate is the
right and due of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> Kings, Parliaments, or Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tats?</p>
            <p>But Sir to returne back againe unto the Oath; I beſeech you let
me aske you, whether are not thoſe men forſworne that have taken the
formenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114264:9"/>Oaths, and then within a little while after
give men commiſſions to fight with, kill and ſlay the very ſame man
they had ſo ſworne unto, for the tenor of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi>
Commiſſion was to kill and ſlay all thoſe that oppoſed him, and in
the head of that Army who oppoſed him was the King, who was as poſſibly
to have been killed in the battle as any other in the Army. Nay Sir, is it not
the higheſt of contradictions, that when you have authorized men three or
foure yeares to fight againſt the King and have taken him priſoner and ſo
keep him, yet you ſhall force men, (although they be freely choſen by their
Country before you will admit them to ſet in your houſe,) to take the fore
recited Oaths to be true to the King: true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my part the Oaths to me are
ſo notablely penned, that I know not with what evaſions or diſtinctions,
you, or any of you that have taken the ſaid Oaths, are able rationally to
free your ſelves, (conſidering your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) from being forſworne and
perjured if a man may ſo call it befor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. I pray you Sir, give me
leave here to recite your late negative Oath, and ſo whether it be not point
blank againſt the Oaths of Allegience and Supremiſie, before recited, the
negitive Oath begins thus,</p>
            <q>I <hi>A. B.</hi> do ſweare from my heart, that I will not
directly nor indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adheare unto or willingly aſſiſt the King in
this Warre or in this cauſe againſt the Parliament, nor any forces raiſed
againſt the two Houſes of Parliament in this Cauſe or Warre, and I do
likewiſe ſweare that my comming and ſubmitting my ſelfe under the power
and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Parliament, is with any manner of deſigne
whatſoever, to the prejudice or proceeding of this preſent Parliament, and
without the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, privity, and adviſe of the King, or any of his
counſell or Officers other then what I have now made knowne, ſo helpe me
God, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this Booke.</q>
            <p>This is the Oath that all the Cavaliers take (or by your orders
ought to take.) before they can make their compoſition, therfor I pray you
let me aske you theſe queſtion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether or no this Oath called the Negative Oath, be not
abſolutly point blanke oppoſit againſt the Oaths called the Oaths of
Suppremiſie and Allegience?</p>
            <p>Secondly, whether or no, are not all thoſe Cavaliers that take
this Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Oath that have taken the two former abſolutly forſworne and
perjur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114264:9"/>and what truſt or confidence is to be put in
perjured Perſons, I leave you to judge;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether or no, are not the Parliament it ſelf
the maine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of theſe mens perjury, in forcing many times this
negative Oath and others upon them againſt their wills, mindes, and
conſciences, and ſo for any thing they know, ſend them headlong to the
devill, which is one of the moſt wickedeſt actions in the world:</p>
            <p>Now Sir to conclude this point; I would faine in the third place
know, how it is poſsible for any of you to ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er in truth, in judgement, and in righteouſneſſe,
as you ought. <hi>Iere.</hi> 4.2. When you take or make Oaths by formes, the
ingredients of which admits in your own underſtandings of various
interpretations, ſo that you are but in a doubting condition, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that
ſenſe you take it be the true ſenſe, or no? and ſo hereby the end of
an Oath is fruſtrate in you, for by Gods appointment, it ought to be the end
of all controvercy and ſtrife. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. but to you theſe Oaths
are but the beginning of them, and ſo in that preticular alone alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
unlawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Seeing Ieſus Chriſt in the fiſt of
<hi>Matth.</hi> 34.35,36,37. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaith, <hi>Sware not at all, neither
by heaven, for it is Gods throne; nor by the earth, for it is his foot-ſtool;
neither by Hieruſalem, for it is the city of the great King. Neither ſhalt
thou ſwear by thy head, becauſe thou canſt not make one haire white or
black. But let your communication be yea, yea, nay, nay; for whatſoever is
more then theſe, commeth of evill.</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Iames,
chap.</hi> 5 12. ſaith, <hi>but above all things my brethren, ſware not
neither by heaven, neither by the earth, neither by any other Oath: but let
your yea, be yea; and your nay, nay; leſt ye fall into
condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing that in all the New Teſtament, there is not the
leaſt rule at all, for any that profeſſe the fear of God, to forſware
at all, in any caſe whatſoever, unleſſe it be, that a ground for
ſwearing can be fetched from that of the ſixth of the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi>
16. which if it can, it is but in one caſe only, namely, <hi>for confirmation
of that truth which a man delivers for the ending of all ſtrife,</hi> as
<hi>I conceive betwixt party, and party,</hi> but that which a man ſwears, he
muſt be ſure of it, and that hee knowes it in his own knowledge to be true,
<hi>or elſe hee ſweares not as God requires, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is truly
obſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114264:10"/>Now Sir, theſe things premiſed and
ſeriouſly conſidered, I deſire to know of you, from whence you, or any
Parliament upon earth fetcheth and derives your Power, Ground, or Authority, to
make and impoſe ſuch formes of Oathes, as the Oathes of Supremacy and
Allegiance are? or the Oathes of your Vowes and Covenants before mentioned are?
that have not only ſo many dubious things in every one of them, but alſo
are expreſly againſt the poſitive command of Chriſt, the Anointed King
of Saints as well as King of kings, and by whom Kings rule; for my part I
proteſt it freely before the God of heaven and earth, I think it as lawful
for me to cut mine own throat, as to take all or any of your fore nentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
unwarrantable Oathes, for he that hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
hath alſo ſaid, <hi>thou ſhalt not in that manner ſwear.</hi> And I
would fain know of you, what confidence the Parliament upon ſollid grounds,
can put upon any men in <hi>England</hi> that are ſo ready and willing to
ſwallow your oat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es? that now are
become nothing elſe but cloaks of knavery, and breeders of ſtrife and
miſchief? therefore for ſhame ſay them all down and preſſe them no
more upon any man whatſoever for he that conſcienſiouſly maks nothing
of an Oath, will make as little of breaking his Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h whenſoever it ſhall make for his profit, eaſe or
preferment, whereas to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m that
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienciouſly ſcruples an Oath, his bare word, promiſe, or
ingagement, is the ſencereſt tye in the world, which he would not willingly
violate for all the earth.</p>
            <p>But Sir, to return to your forementioned grand Objection, That
your Houſes are not in a temper to hear my report and to do me juſtice upon
it, I pray Sir what is the reaſon of it? Is it becauſe there is a Faction
of great men in it that hates my perſon? and therefore though my cauſe be
never ſo juſt, yet they will do me no right? and if ſo, then I tell you
plainly without fear they are a company of Factious knaves, and not a company
of righteous Judges, who ought in judgement to be ſo imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al that they
ſhould not regard or reſpect perſons, but the juſtneſſe of their
cauſe.</p>
            <p>Or Secondly, it is becauſe I have not the Law of the Land
ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on my ſide, and if ſo, it is the eaſier judged againſt
me, but why did you receive and approve of my appeple to your houſe at
firſt, but know Sir, that although I be no Lawyer, yet I dare throw the
gantlet to all the Lawyers in <hi>England;</hi> and againſt them all before
any Legall Barre in <hi>England</hi> will plead my own cauſe my ſelfe, and
juſtifie and prove the Lords proceedings with me, to be point blanke
againſt the good, old, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repealed<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114264:10"/>Law of
<hi>England;</hi> and this I will do at my at moſt, perrell, yea let the
Lords (in the front) put their lying Champion <hi>William Prinn,</hi> the
baſeſt and lyingeſt of men who in leſſ then eight lines, hath told
and print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed twelve or thirteene notorious lyes againſt me, <hi>ſee
Inocencie and truth justified,</hi> page 4. 5. 6. and hath ſuch a firey zeale
to my diſtruction that in his late booke called, <hi>The Sword of Chriſtian
Majestracy ſupported,</hi> hee would have the two Houſes without Law, by
the power of their owne wills to hang me, for no other cauſe in the world,
but for being zealous and couragious in ſtanding for the Laws and Liberties
of <hi>England: which you and he have ſworne, vowed, and covenanted, to
maintaine, preſerve, and defend, and for which you have ſhed</hi> (at
leaſt in pretence) <hi>ſo much Engliſh blood</hi> Oh brave
<hi>Prinn!</hi> a fit man indeed to be a Privy-Counſeller to the great
<hi>Turke.</hi> whoſe will is his Law.</p>
            <p>Or in the third place, it is becauſe the Lords are ſo great
that you dare not do me juſtice and right? for feare of diſpleaſing them,
and if ſo, why doe you not tell the Kingdome ſo (for it is not a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le conſerned in the conteſt betwixt the Lords and my ſelf)
that we may follow your former pattren, to know the names of them, among them
that are enemies to our Liberties and juſt Free ſome, and ſo indeavour to
give them their juſt defer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: For
I read in the 547 548. <hi>pages of the firſt part book Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that
upon a lamentable Petition of many thouſands of pore people in and about the
City of</hi> London, <hi>the Houſe of Commons appoynted a confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with
the Lords, where Mr. Hollis,</hi> whoſe actions demonſtrats there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his
ambition is not to be leſſe then a Duke, or a petty King, though not in
title yet in power and domination <hi>one of the chiefest ſtickler then
against the King, in the whole houſe, (and one of the chiefest Beginners,
Cauſers, and Promoters of the by-paſt warres againſt the King)
preſſed the Lords at there Barre, to joyne with the houſe of Commons in
their deſire about the Militia, and further (with many expreſſions of the
like nature) deſired in words to this effect, that (if that deſire of the
Houſe of Commons were not aſſented too) thoſe Lords who were willing to
concur in would find ſome means to make themſelves knowne, that it might he
knowne who were against them, and they might make it knowne to them who ſent
them: yea in page</hi> 557 <hi>ibim</hi> it is poſitively aver'd, <hi>that he
required the names of all thoſe of that Houſe which</hi> would <hi>not
diſcharge that they then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alledther Kingdom,</hi> ſe the <hi>Juncto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> notable <hi>Declaration</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi>
the ninteenth of <hi>March</hi> 1643. <hi>page</hi> 10. 11. 12. and Mr.
<hi>Hollis</hi> his owne printed Speech, and if this fore recited practis were
juſt then, it is alſo in the like caſe juſt now, yea and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114264:11"/>becauſe our caſe is ten times worſe now then it was
then, and our Lawes and Liberties (principally by the Houſe of Lords means,
and their Arbitrary confederates in the Houſe of Commons) are now a giving up
(to the eyes of all rationall and knowing impartiall men) their laſt breath;
yea, and verily there is but one ſtep betwixt Us the Commons of
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and perfect and abſolute ſlavery, which I for my part had
rather be hanged, if it were poſsible, ten thouſand times over then indure;
but Sir, remember that you in your excellent Declaration of the 19.
<hi>May</hi> 1642. 1. part book Declaration. pag. 207. tell us, <hi>that this
law is as old as the Kingdom, that the Kingdom muſt not be without a means to
preſerve it ſelf;</hi> and I ſay by your own declared principles, that if
you, our ordinary and legall means, will not preſerve us, but rather
deſtroy us, <hi>we may juſtly by extraordinary and rationall means
preſerve our ſelves, and destroy</hi> you <hi>our treacherous
destroyers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or laſtly, is it be cauſe your Houſe hath already done the
laſt Act of Juſtice that ever they intended to doe for the Commons of
<hi>England, (there Impowerers, Lords, and Maſters,)</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I
cannot expect the making of my report: indeed Sir, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gniouſly confeſſe
unto you, I think this is the true reaſon indeed, though you do not in plain
Engliſh words tell us as much, yet by your actions you undeniablely declare
it; for truly many ſay that there is no Iuſtice nor right to be had at your
hands; and for our Laws, they only ſerve you to deſtroy us at your
pleaſure, or to ſerve your ends, when your hot burning malice is incenſed
againſt us; which if they ſerve for your ends, they ſhall be your engines
tu undoe us. But they do not in the leaſt ſerve to defend or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect us
againſt you, but when we ſhould uſe them againſt any of you, as
juſtly we may: See your own excellent <hi>Declaration</hi> of the 26.
<hi>May</hi> 1642. 1 <hi>part book Declar. p.</hi> 278. Sir <hi>Ed. Cookes</hi>
4. <hi>part inſtitut. chap. of the High Court of Parliament;</hi> they are
eſteemed and made by you of no more worth and ſtrength, <hi>then Samſons
green withes, with which he was bound, which at his pleaſure he brook, as a
thred of tow is broken, when it toucheth the fire. Iudg.</hi> 16.9.</p>
            <p>As for inſtance by the 1. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>it is
inacted, That whoſoever ſhall<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114264:11"/>not diligently and
faithfully, having no lawfull or reaſonable excuſe to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
indeavouring themſelves to reſort to their Pariſh-Churches or Chappels
accustomed, or upon reaſonable let thereof, to ſome uſuall place where
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, and ſuch ſervice of God</hi> (marke it well) <hi>ſhall be
uſed, shalbe dealt with as is contained in the foreſaid Statute,</hi> which
Statute is confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>ſtat of the</hi> 23, <hi>Eliz</hi> cap. 1.
<hi>and the penalty increaſed, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re you may read,</hi> which Statutes are alſo <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>firmed by</hi> 29. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 6
&amp; 35. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. Now Sir, I pray you take notice
that theſe and the like laws, doth not ſay, <hi>He that will not come to
Church to hear Sermons, or Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but he that doth not come to ſome
uſuall place where Common Prayer, and ſuch,</hi> (marke that) <hi>ſervice
of God shall be uſed, ſhall be puniſhed ſo and ſo,</hi> as in 1.
<hi>Eliz</hi> chap. 2 and by the 23. <hi>Eliz.</hi> chap 1. <hi>He that doth
not repaire to ſome Church, Chappell, or uſuall place of Common-Prayer,
shall forfeit</hi> 20 l.<hi>a moneth, and be bound to his good behaviour,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>And the other Statutes all refer ſtill, <hi>to the place
where</hi> Common-prayer <hi>is uſed,</hi> ſee the Statute of Conventicles,
being the 35<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Eliz.</hi> chap. 1.</p>
            <p>Now Sir the preſent Parliament having taken away the
Common-Prayer, and ſet up a <hi>Directory,</hi> which theſe lawes never
knew, nor men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the ſting of theſe Lawes are gone in that particular;
for how can I in Iuſtice, be Indited for not comming to heare
<hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> when the Parliament (that now exerciſeth an
abſolute law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and regall power) will not ſuffer it, under ſevere
penalties to be read or remain in being in Pariſh Churches.</p>
            <p>And that the Parliament hath taken away <hi>Common prayer</hi>
appears, by <hi>their printed Ordinance of the third of</hi> January 1644.
<hi>and by their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the twenty three of</hi> Auguſt 1645.
<hi>Booke</hi> Declaration 2 Part, Folio 715. 716. yea in the laſt recited
Ordinance, the Parliament ordaines, <hi>that the ſaid Booke of</hi>
Common-Prayer <hi>ſhould not remaine, or be henceforth uſed in any</hi>
Church, Chappel, <hi>or place of publick Worship within the Kingdom of</hi>
England <hi>and Dominion of Wales, and that the Directory for publick Worship
should be from thenceforth uſe, purſued and obſerved;</hi> And is further
ordained there;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, ſhall at any
time or times hereafter uſe, or cauſe the aforeſaid Book of</hi>
Common-Prayer <hi>to be uſed, in any</hi> Church, Chappell, <hi>or in any
other publick place of Worship, or in any other private place or Family
whatſoever within<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114264:12"/>the Kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>and
Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>that then every ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Perſon offending
therein, ſhall for the firſt offence for fit the ſum of</hi> 5. l.<hi>for
the ſecond offence the ſum of ten pound, and for the third offence, ſhall
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer one whole yeares impriſonment, without baile or main
priſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it therefurther ordained, <hi>that all Common-Prayer Bookes
remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Churches or Chappells, ſhall within a moneth after the
puliſhing of this Ordinance, be by the Church-Wardens, &amp;c. under the
penalty of forty shilling carried unto the Committes of the reſpective
Countries, where they ſhall be found, to be diſpoſed of as the Parliament
ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides the Parliament by Order and Ordinance, hath not as
yet to this day appointed any puniſhment at all, for men that doe not come to
their pariſh Churches or Chapples to heare ſermons, or the
<hi>Directory,</hi> or that meet in privat houſes, commonly called
Convinticles: Therefore though I ſtay ſeven yeares from Church, and
conſtantly meet in private houſes, there is by the Parliaments principalls
neither Law nor Ordinance in force for any Judge or Juſtices of the Peace to
indict me or any other, or any otherwiſe to moleſt or troub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e me.</p>
            <p>And as for the Ordinance of the 26 of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1645 and the
Order of the Houſe of Commons, the 31 of <hi>December</hi> 1646 <hi>they
onely declare they diſlike and their intentions to proceed againſt all
ſuch perſons as ſhall take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to preach, or expound the
Scriptures in any Church or Chappell, or any other publike place, except they
be ordained either here, or in ſome other reformed Churches, &amp;c.</hi> but
it ſaith not a word to any of thoſe that heare them, or any that comes not
to their pariſh Churches but meet in privat houſes, neither doth it
authoriſe any Judges, Juſtices of peace, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons
whatſoever, to puniſh thoſe unordained preaching perſons, <hi>but
reſerves the power of puniſhment to themſelves, without declaring as yet
what it is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding all this, <hi>That all men that uſe
the Common-Prayer, are liabell to the puniſhments before recited,</hi>
multitudes of hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, godly conſciencious perſons well-affected men to
the Parliament, &amp; who have ventred al they have for its preſervation, are
continually indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and puniſhed by the Parliaments Judges and Juſtices
of peace, for not comming to there <hi>Pariſh Churches to heare common
prayer,</hi> for there are no other Statutes to authoriſe them to puniſh
any for not comming to their pariſh Churches, but thoſe <hi>very Common
prayer Statutes,</hi> O brave Parliament Juſtice, what is this elſe but
perfect ingling, or playing at <hi>Hocus po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:114264:12"/>Sir, I beſeech you let me aske you this
queſtion, if an Ordinance of Parliament be not as ſtrongly valievd, and as
forciable to take away a Law, as coutrary to the Law, to create and impower a
Judge or Juſtice to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute a Law in force? and whether or no that Judge
that is made by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Parliament be not an abſolute Murtherer, and a
Contemner of the Parliaments authoritie. <hi>(in the opinion of all that hold
the preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments principalls,)</hi> if he ſhall take away a mans
life, or otherwiſe puniſh him for tranſgreſſing of a Law, which the
Parliament by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance hath taken away, and I ſaid a ſever penalty upon
any man that ſhall obſerue or doe the thing injoyned and commanded by that
Law? <hi>&amp;</hi> how can a Judge in tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and righteouſneſſe ſweare to execute the Law
when hee hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not al w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> power in him, but is made by a power
oppoſet to the Law, ſee the 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.24.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place by the Statutes of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6 chap.
12. &amp;. 39. <hi>Eliz.</hi> chap. 15. <hi>the ſtealing of Horſes,
Geldings, or Mares, and the fellonous ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away in the day time</hi> (as
well as the night,) <hi>of any money, goods, or cattle, being of the value of
five ſhillings, or upwards, in any dwelling houſe or houſes, or any part
thereof, or any out-houſe or out-houſes be longing, and uſed to, and with
any dwelling houſe or houſes, although no perſon ſhall be in the ſaid
houſe or out-houſes, at the time of ſuch fellonie committed, ſhall in
both caſes looſe the benifit of their Clergy, and die without
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet the preſent Parliament gives authority to divers
perſons; to doe both the forementioned things, that is to ſay, <hi>to take
horſes and goods away by force, againſt the wills and minds of the
Owners,</hi> and that before they be legally convicted, of any crime, which
although they ſweare to maintaine the Law, yet this is abſolutly againſt
the Law, as Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> there owne magnified <hi>author</hi> in
his <hi>third part inſtituts chapter</hi> 103. <hi>folio</hi> 228. declares,
which Booke is publiſhed by their own authority and command, and he there
expreſſely ſaith, <hi>that regalarly the goods &amp;c. of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Delinquent
cannot be taken and ſeized to the Kings uſe, before the ſame be
fofited.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the ſame cannot be inuentoried, and the Towne
charged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi> before the Owner be indicted of record.</p>
            <p>And amongſt other authorities, as <hi>Britton, Fleta,
Bracton,</hi> &amp;c. which he there makes uſe of, he fites the 1
<hi>Richard</hi> the third chapter 3. <hi>by which it is inacted and declared
that neither Shriffe</hi> Eſcheater <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe,<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114264:13"/>of
franchiſe,</hi> or any other perſon take or ſeize <hi>the goods of any
perſon arrested, or impriſoned for ſuſpiton of fellony, before he be
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed or attaint of the fellony, according to the lawes of</hi> England,
<hi>or before the goods be other wiſe lawfully forfeited upon paine to
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit double the value of the goods ſo taken to the party grieved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which and the other Authorities he there makes uſe of, he
ſaith theſe two concluſions are manifeſtly proved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>that before indictment, the goods or other things of
any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender cannot be ſearched, inventored, or in any ſort ſeized, nor
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indictment ſeized, and removed, or taken away before conviction or
attainder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>that the begging of the goods or ſtate of any</hi>
Delinquent <hi>accuſed or indicted of any treaſon, fellony, or any other
offence, before he be convicted and attainted, is utterly unlawfull, becauſe
before conviction and attainder, as hath been ſaid, nothing is forfeited to
the King, nor grantable by him: And beſides it either maketh the
proſecution againſt the</hi> Delinquent <hi>more principitate, violent, and
undue, then the guiet and eqaall Proceeding of the Law and Juſtice would
permit, or elſe by ſome under-hand compoſſition and agreement ſtop or
hinder the due courſe of Juſtice, for examplary Puniſhment of the
Offender.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, <hi>(ſaith he) when the</hi> Delinquent <hi>is
begged, it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth both Judge, Jurour, and Witneſſe, to doe their
duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet for all this, many times the Souldiers imployed by the
Commanders of the Parliaments preſents warre, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and inioyned be
their Commanders authoriſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by authoritie derived from the
Parliament, <hi>to take away Horſes goods, &amp;c.</hi> for the
ſupportation and preſervation of the preſent forces, which it may be at
that time were in great neceſſitie and danger, and the ſouldiers
refuſing in that particuler to obey his or there Commander might by the
Articles of Warre made by Ordinance of Parliament hazard his life, yea and it
may be actually hanged firſt, yet poore men when the Parliament have ſerved
their turnes of him or them, to pay him his Arreares, for all his hazards and
dangers, hee is by their Judges and Miniſters (made be the Parliament it 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114264:13"/>ſelfe) for the very fore-mentioned actions done in
obedience to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, arraigned, indicted, and hanged as a fellon
therefore; ſee the Marginall Notes of the ſecond Apology of Sir <hi>Thomas
Fairfax</hi>'s Souldiers, (this is juſt as the builders of <hi>Noa</hi>'s
Arke were ſerved) for (or after) their making it: Oh ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Parliamentary
Juſtice! worthy for their praiſe to be recorded to future Generations, as
an everlaſting memoriall of their unpreſidented juſtice and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude;
and yet if any particular man of the Parliament, or any of their vermine
Catchpoles, have a ſpleen at a man, it is eaſie for him to get a Warrant
from the Chaire-man of ſome particular private Committee, to go and ſearch
ſuch a mans houſe that never profeſſed enmity againſt the juſt
proceedings of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and breake open his doors, and take away (at their
pleaſure) ſo many or much of his proper goods, as they pleaſe; Oh pure
Juſtice! without ſpot or blemiſh!</p>
            <p>Nay, any of their Catchpole Rogues or Caterpillars can forceably
enter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny freemans houſe, when n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne is in it, and load away divers Porters with his proper goods,
and that without the ſeeming Authority of any Law or Statute, Order, or
Ordinance of Parliament, nay without the Warrant of any private Committee,
though in Law ſuch a Committees Order is not worth one ſtraw;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, and when this is complained of
to a Committee of Parliament, not one
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ram of juſtice can be had for
it: And truly Sir, beſides other inſtances of this, I will onely aver it to
be lately my owne, for one of M. <hi>Corbets</hi> and Juſtice
<hi>Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Catchpoles (<hi>Whitaker</hi> the Bookſeller in
<hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard London) did the very forementioned thing to me, of
which I complained at my laſt being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Committee of your Houſe, but
could not have one dram of Juſtice, though
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſſed it hard; ſee the
relation of it in print, called <hi>The reſolved mans Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
pag.</hi> 12. 13.</p>
            <p>Sir, I pray, is not this unſpotted Juſtice? and yet, is it not
as good as the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of that which now adaies flowes from both
Houſes?</p>
            <p>In the third place, by the Statute of the 27. <hi>Eliz. Chap.</hi>
2. <hi>it is inacted that all and every Jeſuites, Seminary Prieſts,</hi>
and other Prieſts whatſoever (marke the word whatſoever) <hi>made and
ordained out of the Realme of England, or other her
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighneſſe Dominions, or within
any of her Majeſties Realmes, or Dominions,</hi> marke well the word within,
<hi>by any Authority, Power or Juriſdiction, derived, challenged,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pretended from the See of Rome
ſince the firſt yeare of her Reigne, ſhall within forty daies after the
end of that Seſſion of Parliament, depart out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, <hi>That it ſhall not be lawfull to
or far any Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary
Prieſt, or other ſuch Prieſt, Deacon, or religious or Eccleſiaſlicall
perſon whatſoever, being borne within this Realme, or any other her
highneſſe Dominions, and<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114264:14"/>heretofore ſince the ſaid
Feaſt of the nativity of S.</hi> John <hi>Baptiſt, in the firſt yeare of
her Majeſties Reigne, made, ordained, or profeſsed or hereafter</hi> (marke
the word here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) <hi>to be made, ordained, or profeſsed by any Authority,
or Juriſdiction, derived, challenged or pretended from the See of Rome, by or
of what name, title or degree ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſame ſhall be called or known,
to come into, be or remaine in anie part of this Realm, &amp;c.</hi> (mark the
laſt ſentence well) <hi>after the end of forty daies, otherwiſe then in
ſuch ſpeciall caſes, and upon ſuch ſpeciall occaſions onely, and
for ſuch time only as is expreſsed in this Act: and if he doe, that then
every ſuch offence ſhall be taken and adjudged to be high Treaſon, and
every perſon ſo offending, ſhall for his offence be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Traytor,
and ſhall ſuffer loſſe, and forfeit as in caſe of high
Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is there further enacted, <hi>That whoſoever ſhall
wittingly or willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, relieve, comfort, aid or maintaine any ſuch
perſon before-mentioned, being at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty out of priſon, knowing him to be
ſuch as before is expreſſed, ſhall alſo for ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be
adjudged a fellon, without benefit of Clergie, and ſuffer death, loſe and
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits, as in caſe of one attainted of Fellony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Parliament hath made a ſolemne League and Covenant, and
voted, <hi>that no man ſhall ſit in Parliament without taking it, nor no
man beare any Office with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking it, and you have voted, and in ſeverall
places made the Freemen of England uncapable to give a voice to chooſe an
Officer, if they will not take it;</hi> in the ſecond Article of which
unjuſt, unrighteous and wicked contradicting Covenant, all thoſe that take
it, <hi>ſweare to extirpate Popery,</hi> 1 <hi>part Book Deel. fol.</hi> 425.
and yet notwithſtanding the Judges and Juſtices of peace made by the
preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, force the Freemen of England againſt their wills and
minds, and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation of the fore-mentioned Law and Covenant, to pay
Tythes <hi>(the root and ſupport of Popery)</hi> to a generation of new
upſtart Romiſh Prieſts, (or Synodian Sion Colledge <hi>Jure divino</hi>
men) that have no other Authority and Power to ſtand by in their function of
Presbyterie, but what they challenge and derive from Rome, having alreadie
avowedly in print renounced and ſcorned any Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, either from the
Parliament, or the people of their Pariſhes, by vertue of which their owne
avowed claime, they are <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> within the laſh and reach of
the fore-mentioned Statute, and <hi>may by any Freeman of England be indicted
at the Aſſizes or Seſſions, for Traytors, and ought without mercy (by
the ſtrength of that Law) to ſuffer as Traytors;</hi> and all thoſe that
pay Tythes or otherwiſe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them, <hi>after they know they have
renounced the</hi> deriving of their Power and Juriſdiction from the
Parliament, and challenge it <hi>Jure divino,</hi> derivitive from the Pope,
<hi>may be indicted as Fellons, and ought to die as Fellons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, is it not a piece of gallant juſtice in the Parliaments
Judges, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and illegall Committee-men? to put freemens perſons in
priſon without Baile or Maineprize, and to plunder (and I think I may ſay
rob) divers of them<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114264:14"/>of their goods and cattels, <hi>for
refuſing to ſupport Popery</hi> (after they have ſworne to extirpate it)
by paying of Tythes to a company of Popiſh Presbyterian Prieſts, that
ſcorne to derive any power from the people of their Pariſhes, and have
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready publikely and avowedly renounced the Parliaments Power and Authority,
and doe actually and really claime and aſſume unto themſelves <hi>an
Eccleſiaſticall or Clergie Authority derivitive from Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly the Law of England hath provided an univerſall remedy,
for all the men of England to recover their debts by, from thoſe that are
indebted to them, the benefit of which Law, the preſent Parliament both doe
and will injoy, and at their pleaſure will ſue anie freeman in England that
is not one of themſelves, <hi>but are ſo fortified with their big ſwolne
priviledges,</hi> that no man ſhall dare to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle either with their
perſons or eſtates, though they owe never ſo much, and yet divers of them
will neither (of themſelves) pay uſe nor principall, although o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally
the exemption of their perſons from Arreſts be not a priviledge given them
for themſelves in reference to their particulars, <hi>but for the good of the
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and People that chooſe them,</hi> that ſo by the malice of any
prerogative man, or enemy to the juſt Libertie of the Commons of England,
they might not by malicious Arreſts be moleſted, troubled diverted or
hindered, for doing their Countrey faithfull ſervice in the place they had
choſen them unto: But when this priviledge was firſt given them, (which in
its ſelfe is juſt in its inſtitution, though now by the preſent
Parliament-men abuſed in its execution, it remained in them but for certaine
weeks, for then Parliaments were very ſhort, being by the ancient and juſt
unrepealed Law of the Land, to be choſen once every year or oftner if need
required, 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3.14. &amp; 36. <hi>E.</hi> 3.10. it being
impoſſible to be conceived that ever they thought then, that any Parliament
in England ſhould remaine ſeven years to the cheating, cozening, and
devouring of particular mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of men of their particular debts, which now
are likely by ſome Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-men, to be ſo long owing them, that they
will not be claimable or reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable by Law, when this Parliament is ended,
which by its long ſitting is, and is more evidently like to be the greateſt
ſubverſion of Englands Lawes, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Freedomes, of any thing that
ever was done in England: King <hi>Charles</hi> his ſeventeen years
miſ-government before this Parliament (as you in your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations call it)
was <hi>but a flea-biting, or as a mouldhill to a mountain, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of
what this everlaſting Parliament</hi> already is, and will be to the whole
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and therefore I ſay, and will maintaine it upon the loſſe of
my life, that the Commons of England may bid adieu to their Lawes, Liberties,
Freedomes, Trades and Properties, <hi>unleſſe they ſpeedily take a
courſe for the electing of a new Parliament,</hi> for the Members of this
Parliament (many of them to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) judge themſelves ſubject to no
rule, <hi>nor to be governed by any law,</hi> but ſay,<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114264:15"/>that they are above <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the moſt excellent
Petition of Right, and may aboliſh them, although there be divers things in
them ſo founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the principles of pure reaſon, (which by the
fundamentall Maximes of the Law are unalterable, Doctor and Student,
<hi>Ch.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 4, 5. ſee <hi>Innocency and truth juſtified,
p.</hi> 62.) and the Morall Law of God, that it is impoſſible for any power
whatſoever to aboliſh them, that is not greater then God, or hath not
derived a juſt power from him to diſpence with his unchangeable Lawes, one
of which is, <hi>That Juſtice ſhall never be ſold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor impartially
adminiſtred,</hi> which is with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt excellent, rationall and
unalterable things ratified expreſſely, in the 29. <hi>Ch.</hi> of
<hi>Magna Charta, beſides all the reſt of moſt excellent things</hi> in
thoſe two Lawes confirmed, many of which are of univerſall concernment to
all the ſons of men, under any juſt Government in the world: and as for
thoſe things contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, that are rationally in proceſſe of time
upon juſt experimentall grounds alterable, and changeable, if you will give
us better in their places, doe when you will, without the doing of which by
your own grounds and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, you cannot juſtly change them, <hi>being
impowered and choſen by us to provide for our weale, but not for our woe, to
provide for our better being, but not for our worſe being.</hi> 1 <hi>part
Book Dec. p.</hi> 150.</p>
            <p>Againe, fifthly, the Law of England hath provided, <hi>That
whoſoever breaks the peace ſhall be puniſhed, or whoſoever layes
violent hands upon a man,</hi> and if any man doe it to a Parliament-man he
will trounce him for it, but they themſelves can breake the peace, and lay
violent hands without cauſe upon the Freemen of England, and then make what
lying reports to the Houſe they pleaſe, and get their bodies committed to
priſon, and that without hearing them, and all this did M. <hi>Hollis</hi>
and Sir <hi>Walter Earl</hi> the other day to Major <hi>Tuliday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, ſixthly, you your ſelves have declared, <hi>that you
have received Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the removall of things eſtabliſhed by Law,
and</hi> (ſay you) <hi>we muſt ſay, that all that know what belongeth to
the courſe and practice of Parliament will ſay, that we ought ſo to doe,
and that our Predeceſſors and his Majeſties Anceſtors have conſtantly
done it, there being no other place wherein Lawes that by experience may be
found grievous and burthenſome can be altered or repealed, and there being no
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther due and legall way, wherein they which are aggrieved by them can ſeeke
redreſſe;</hi> 1 <hi>part Book Dec. p.</hi> 720. Yea, and in ſeverall of
your Declarations you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and maintained, <hi>that the concourſe
of people at Weſtminſter to deliver and waite for anſwer to their
Petitions is both juſt and lawfull,</hi> 1 <hi>part Booke Dec. p.</hi> 123.
201. 209.</p>
            <p>And yet now of late you are growne to that paſſe, that you
reject and will not receive Petitions if they croſſe your humours, although
they be for nothing but the obtaining Juſtice, according to the juſt and
unrepealed long practiſed Law<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114264:15"/>of England, and this was the
caſe of the honeſt Buckinghamſhire and Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire men in their late
Petition: ſee the ſcond Edition of the <hi>Outcries of oppreſſed
Commons, p.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Yea, and when divers honeſt Citizens of London, and as firme
friends to you in the day of your ſtraits as any was in England, were about a
Petition for <hi>the redreſſe of divers things amiſſe, and the
eſtabliſhment of their juſt Lawes and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for which divers of
them by your command, have freely ventured their lives:</hi> the Petition by
one of your informing Catchpoles, was ſtollen out of M. <hi>Thomas
Lamb's</hi> houſe, and by M. <hi>Glyn</hi> Recorder of London, and one of
your owne Members brought into your Houſe, and there in a great heat voted
(as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) a ſeditious paper, which whether it be ſo or no, let
the world judge by the copie of it, which thus followeth.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the right honourable and ſupreme Authority of this
Nation, the Commons in PARLIAMENT aſſembled. The humble Petition of many
thouſands, carneſtly deſiring the glory of God, the freedome of the
Common-wealth, and the peace of all men.</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat as no Civill Government is more juſt in the
conſtitution, then that of Parliaments, having its foundation in the free
choice of the people; and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he
end of all Government is the ſafetie and freedome of the governed, even
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o the people of this Nation in all
times have manifeſted moſt heartie affections into Parliaments as the
moſt proper remedie of their grievances; yet ſuch hath
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>een the wicked policies of thoſe
who from time to time have endeavoured to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ring this Nation into bondage;
that they have in all times either by the diſuſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r abuſe of <hi>Parliaments</hi>
deprived the people of their hopes: For teſtimony whereof the late times
foregoing this <hi>Parliament</hi> will ſadly witneſſe, when it was not
onely made a crime to mention a <hi>Parliament,</hi> but either the pretended
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>egative voice, (the moſt
deſtructive to freedome) or a ſpeedie diſſolution, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ed the fruit and benefit thereof,
whilſt the whole Land was overſpread with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll kinds of oppreſsions and
tyranny, extending both to ſoule and body, and that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n ſo rooted and ſetled a way,
that the complaints of the people in generall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſsed, that they would have given any thing in the
world for one ſix moneths <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>eedome of <hi>Parliament.</hi> Which hath been ſince evidenced in
their inſtant &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tant
readineſſe of aſſiſtance to this preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi>
excee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing the Records
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f former ages, and wherein God
hath bleſſed them with their firſt deſires, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <pb n="30" facs="tcp:114264:16"/>this <hi>Parliament</hi> the moſt abſolute and free of any
<hi>Parliament</hi> that ever was and enabling it with power ſufficient to
deliver the whole Nation from all kind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of oppreſſions and grievances, though of very long
continuance, and to make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the
moſt abſolute and free Nation in the world.</p>
                        <p>And it is moſt thankfully acknowledged that ye have in
order to the freedom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of the people
ſuppreſſed the high Commiſsion, Star-Chamber, and Councell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Table, called home the baniſhed,
delivered ſuch as were impriſoned for matter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of conſcience, and brought ſome Delinquents to
deſerved puniſhment. That y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
have ſuppreſſed the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Popiſh <hi>Lords,</hi>
aboliſhed <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and that kind of Prelatick perſecuting
government. That ye have taken away Ship-money and all the new illegall
Patents, whereby the hearts of all the well-affected were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged and filled
with a confident hope, that they ſhould have ſeen long ere thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> a compleat removall of all grievances,
and the whole people delivered from all oppreſſions over ſoule or body:
But ſuch is our miſerie that after the expenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of ſo much precious time, of blood and treaſure,
and the ruine of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of honeſt families in recovering our
Liberties, we ſtill find this Nation op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with grievances of the
ſame deſtructive nature as formerly, though unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> other notions; and which are ſo much the more
grievous unto us, becauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
are inflicted in the very time of this preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> under God
the hope o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the oppreſſed. For,
as then all the men and women in <hi>England</hi> were made lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the
ſummons, attachments, ſentences, and impriſonments of the Lords o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the Councell-boord, ſo we find by
wofull experience and ſufferings of many pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, that the preſent Lords doe aſſume and
exerciſe the ſame pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, then which nothing is, or can be more repugnant
and deſtructive to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons juſt liberties.</p>
                        <p>As then the unjuſt power of <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> was
exerciſed in compelling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> men
and women to anſwer to Interrogatoties tending to accuſe themſelves
an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> others; ſo is the ſame now
frequently practiced upon divers perſons, even yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> cordiall friends that have been, and
ſtill are puniſhed for refuſing to anſwer
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> queſtions againſt
themſelves, and neareſt relations. As then the great oppreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the high Commiſſion was
moſt evident in moleſting of godly peaceab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> people, for non-conformity, or different opinion and practice in
Religion, jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all who were
contrary-minded to themſelves, to bee Hereticks, Sectarie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Schiſmaticks, ſeditious, factious,
enemies to the State, and the like; and und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> great penalties forbidding all perſons, not licenced by them, to
preach or pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Goſpel:
Even ſo now at this day, the very ſame, if not greater moleſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are ſet on foot, and violently
proſecuted by the inſtigation of a Clergy n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> more infallible then the former, to the extreame diſcouragement
and affliction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> many
thouſands of your faithfull adherents, who are not ſatisfied that contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies <pb n="31" facs="tcp:114264:16"/>in
Religion, can be truſted to the compulſive regulation of any: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the Biſhops were ſuppreſſed, did hope never to have ſeen ſuch a
power aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by any in this Nation any more.</p>
                        <p>And although all new illegal Patents are by you
aboliſhed, yet the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Monopoly of Merchant-adventurers, and
others, do ſtill remain to the great abridgement of the liberties of the
people, and to the extreme prejudice of all ſuch induſtrious people as
depend on cloathing, or other woollen manufacture, (it being the Staple
commodity of this Nation,) and to the great diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and
diſadvantage of all ſorts of Tradeſmen, Sea-faring-men, and hindrance of
Shipping and Navigation. Alſo the old tedious and chargable way of deciding
controverſies, or ſuits in Law, is continued to this day, to the extreame
vexation and utter undoing of multitudes of Families; a grievance as great and
as palpable as any in the world. Likewiſe, that old, but moſt unequall
puniſhment of malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, is ſtill continued, whereby mens lives and
liberties are as liable to the law, and corporall pains as much inflicted for
ſmall as for great offences, and that moſt unjuſtly upon the reſtimony
of one witneſſe, contrary both to the law of God, and common equity, a
grievance very great, but litle regarded. Alſo tythes, and other enforced
maintenance are ſtill continued, though there be no ground for either under
the Goſpel; and though the ſame have occaſioned multitudes of ſuites,
quarrels and debates, both in former and latter times. In like maner,
mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of poore diſtreſſed priſoners for debt, ly ſtill
unregarded, in a moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and wofull condition throughout the Land,
to the great reproach of this Nation. Likewiſe Priſon-Keepers, or Goalers,
are as preſumptuous as ever they were, both in receiving and detaining of
Priſoners illegally committed, as cruell and inhumane to all, eſpecially to
ſuch as are well-affected, as oppreſſive and extorting in their Fees, and
are attended with under-officers, of ſuch vile and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian demeanour,
as is moſt abominable. Alſo thouſands of men and women are ſtill (as
formerly) permit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>d to live in
beggery and wickedneſſe all their life long, and to breed their children to
the ſame idle and vitious courſe of life, and no effectual meanes uſed to
reclaim either, or to reduce them to any vertue or induſtry.</p>
                        <p>And laſt, as thoſe who found themſelves aggrieved
formerly at the burdens &amp; oppreſſions of thoſe times, that did not
conform to the Church-government then eſtabliſhed, refuſed to pay
Ship-money, or yeeld obedience to unjuſt Patents, were reviled and reproached
with nicknames of Puritans, Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, Sectaries, or were
tearmed factious or ſeditious, men of turbulent ſpirits, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of
government, and diſturbers of the publike peace; even ſo is it at this day
in all reſpects, with thoſe who ſhew any ſenſibility of the
fore-recited grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or move in any manner or meaſure for remedy
thereof, all the reproaches,<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114264:17"/>evills, and miſchiefs that
can be deviſed, are thought too few or too little to bee ſaid upon them, as
Roundheads, Sectaries, Independents, Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, factious,
ſeditious, rebellious diſturbers of the publike peace, deſtroyers of all
eivill relation, and ſubordinations; yea, and beyond what was formerly,
non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity is now judged a ſufficient cauſe to diſable any perſon
though of known fidelity, from bearing any Office of truſt in the
Common-wealth, whileſt Neuters, Malignants, and diſ-affected are admitted
and continued. And though it be not now made a crime to mention a
<hi>Parliament,</hi> yet is it little leſſe to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſupreme power
of this honourable Houſe. So that in all theſe reſpects, this Nation
remaineth in a very ſad and diſconſolate condition; and the more,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is thus with us after ſo long a ſeſſion of ſo powerfull
and ſo free a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and which hath been ſo made and
maintained, by the aboundant love and liberall effuſion of the blood of the
people. And therefore knowing no danger nor thraldome like unto our being left
in this moſt ſad condition by this <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and obſerving
that we are now drawing the great and weighty affaires of this Nation to ſome
kind of concluſion, and fearing that ye may ere long bee obſtructed by
ſomthing equally evill to a negative voice, and that ye may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to
lay by that ſtrength, which (under God) hath hitherto made you pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull to
all good workes: whileſt we have yet time to hope, and yee power to help, and
leaſt by our ſilence we might be guilty of that ruine and ſlavery, which
without your ſpeedy help is like to fall upon us, your ſelves and the whole
Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; we have perſumed to ſpread our cauſe thus plainely and largely
before you: And do moſt earneſtly entreat, that ye will ſtir up your
affections to a zealous love and tender regard of the people, who have choſen
and truſted you, and that ye will ſeriouſly conſider, that the end of
their truſt, was freedome and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from all kind of temporall
grievances and oppreſſions.</p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. And that therefore in the firſt place, ye will
bee exceeding carefull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your juſt authority from all prejudices
of a negative voice in any perſon or perſons whomſoever, which may
diſable you from making that happy return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people which they
juſtly expect, and that ye will not be induced to lay by your ſtrength,
untill ye have ſatisfied your underſtandings in the undoubted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
of your ſelves, and of thoſe who have voluntarily and faithfully adhered
unto you in all your extremities; and untill yee have ſecured and ſetled
the Common-wealth in ſolid peace and true freedome, which is the end of the
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive inſtitution of all governments.</item>
                           <item>2. That ye will take off all Sentences, Fines and
Impriſonments impoſed on Commoners, by any whomſoever, without due
courſe of Law, or judgement of their equalls: and to give due reparations to
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l thoſe who have been ſo
injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly dealt withall, and for preventing the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ke for the time to come, that yee<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114264:17"/>will enact all ſuch Arbitrary proceedings to bee capitall
crimes.</item>
                           <item>3. That ye will permit no authority whatſoever, to
compell any [perſon or perſons to anſwer to queſtions againſt
themſelves, or neareſt relations, except in caſes of private intereſt
between party and party in a legall way, and to releaſe all ſuch as
ſuffer by impriſonment, or otherwiſe for refuſing to anſwer to ſuch
Interrogatories.</item>
                           <item>4. That all Statutes, Oathes and Covenants may be
repealed ſo farre as they tend, or may be conſtrued to the moleſtation
and enſnaring of religious, peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, well-affected people, for
non-conformity, or different opinion or practice in Religion.</item>
                           <item>5. That no man for preaching or publiſhing his
opinion in Religion in a peaceable way, may be puniſhed or perſecuted as
hereticall, by Judges that are not infallible, but may be miſtaken (as well
as other men) in their judgements, leaſt upon pretence of ſuppreſſing
Errors, Sects or Schiſms, the moſt neceſſary truths, and ſincere
profeſſors thereof may be ſuppreſſed, as upon the like pretence it
hath been in all ages.</item>
                           <item>6. That ye will, for the encouragement of
induſtrious people, diſſolve that old oppreſſive Company of
Merchant-Adventurers, and the like, and prevent all ſuch others by great
penalties for ever.</item>
                           <item>7. That yee will ſettle a juſt, ſpeedy, plaine
and unburthenſome way, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding of controverſies and ſuits in Law,
and reduce all Lawes to the neareſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with Chriſtianity, and
publiſh them in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, and that all proceſſes and
proceedings therein may be true and alſo in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and in the
moſt uſuall Character of writing, without any abreviations, that each one
who can read, may the better underſtand their owne affaires; and that the
duty of all Judges, Officers, and practicers in the Law, and of all
Magiſtrates and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the Common-wealth may be preſcribed, and their
fees limited underſtrict penalties, and publiſhed in print to the view and
knowledge of all men: by which juſt and equitable meanes, this Nation ſhall
be for ever freed of an oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion more burthenſome and troubleſome
then all the oppreſſions hitherto by this <hi>Parliament</hi>
removed.</item>
                           <item>8. That the life of no perſon may be taken away,
under the teſtimony of two witneſſes at leaſt, of honeſt
converſation; and that in an equitable way ye will proportion puniſhments
to offences, that ſo no mans life may be taken, his body puniſhed, nor his
eſtate forfeited, but upon ſuch weighty and conſiderable cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as
juſtly deſerve ſuch puniſhments; and that all priſoners may have a
ſpeedy tryall, that they be neither ſtarved, nor their families ruined, by
long and lingring impriſonment; and that impriſonment may be uſed onely
ſafe cuſtody untill time of triall, and not as a puniſhment for
offences.</item>
                           <item>
                              <pb n="34" facs="tcp:114264:18"/>9. That tythes and all other
enforced maintenance, may be for ever aboliſhed, and nothing in place thereof
impoſed; but that all Miniſters may be paid onely by thoſe who
voluntarily contribute to them, or chuſe them, and contract with them for
their labours.</item>
                           <item>10. That ye will take ſome ſpeedy and effectuall
courſe to relieve all ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners for debt, as are altogether unable
to pay, that they may not periſh in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon through the
hard-heartedneſſe of their Creditors; and that all ſuch as have any
eſtates, may bee inforced to make paiment accordingly, and not to ſhelter
themſelves in priſon to defraud their Creditors.</item>
                           <item>11. That none may be Priſon-keepers, but ſuch as
are of approved honeſtie, and that they may be prohibited under great
penalties to receive or detaine any perſon or perſons without lawfull
warrant: That their uſage of priſoners may be with gentleneſſe and
civility, their fees moderate and certain, and that they may give ſecurity
for the good behaviour of their under-Officers.</item>
                           <item>12. That ye will provide ſome powerfull meanes to
keep men, women, and children from begging and wickedneſſe, that this
Nation may be no longer a ſhame to Chriſtianity therein.</item>
                           <item>13. That ye will reſtraine and diſcountenance the
malice and impudency of impious perſons, in their reviling and reproaching
the well-affected, with the ignominious titles of Round-heads, factious,
ſeditious and the like, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by your reall friends have been a long time,
and ſtill are exceedingly wronged, diſcouraged, and made obnoxious to rude
and prophane people, and that ye wil not exclude any of approved fidelity from
bearing office of truſt in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth for non-conformity; but rather
Neuters and ſuch as manifeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection or oppoſition to common
freedome, the admiſſion and continuation of ſuch being the chief cauſe
of all theſe our grievances.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Theſe remedies, or what other ſhall ſeem more
effectuall to your grave wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, we humbly pray may be ſpeedily applied,
and that in doing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ye will be confident of the aſſiſtance of
your Petitioners, and of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate well-minded people, to the
uttermoſt of their beſt abilities, againſt all oppoſition whatſoever,
looking upon our ſelves as more concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned now at laſt to make a good end,
then at the firſt to have made a good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: For what ſhall it profit
us, or what remedy can we expect, if now after ſo great troubles and
miſeries this Nation ſhould be left by this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in ſo great a
thraldome, both of body, mind, and eſtate?</p>
                        <p>We beſeech you therefore, that with all your might
whileſt he have time, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power, ſo effectually to fulfill the
true end of Parliaments in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering this Nation from theſe and all other
grievances, but none may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume or da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> to introduce the like for ever.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114264:18"/>And we truſt, the God of your good
ſucceſſe, will manifeſt the integrity of our intentions herein, and
that our humble deſires are ſuch, as tend not onely to our owne particular,
but to the generall good of the Common-wealth, and proper for this Honourable
Houſe to grant, without which this Nation cannot be ſafe, or happy: And
that he will bleſſe you with true Chriſtian fortitude, ſuitable to the
truſt and greatneſſe of the worke yee have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, and make the
memory of this Parliament bleſſed to all ſucceeding Generations.</p>
                        <closer>Shall ever be the fervent deſire o your humble
Petitioners.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And the Prerogative-men of <hi>London,</hi> which are ready to be
Aſſociates with you in inſlaving the people, petition againſt it, and
had thanks returned to them for it; and M. <hi>Lamb</hi> ſent up for to a
Committee as a Delinquent, and divers hundreds of his Fellow-petitioners came
up with him, with a Certificate to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow the Petition, which was as
followeth.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <head>To the honourable the Committee of Parliament ſitting
in the Queens Court at Weſtminſter, Colonell <hi>Lee</hi> being Chaire-man,
The humble Certificate of divers perſons here preſent intereſted in, and
avouching the Petition lately referred to this Committee by the right
honourable the Houſe of Commons:</head>
                        <opener>Humbly certifying,</opener>
                        <p>THat the Petition entituled, <hi>The humble Petition of
many thouſands earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſiring the glory of God, the freedome of the
Common-wealth, and the peace of all men; and directed to the right honourable
and ſupreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Nation, the Commons in Parliament
aſſembled,</hi> Is no ſcandalous or ſeditious Paper, as hath been
unjuſtly ſuggeſted, but a reall Petition, ſubſcribed, and to be
ſubſcribed by none but conſtant cordiall friends to Parliament and
Common-wealth, and to be preſented to that honourable Houſe with all
poſſible ſpeed, as an eſpeciall meanes to procure the univerſall good
of this long inthralled and diſtracted Nation. And we truſt this honourable
Committee will in no meaſure diſhearten the People from preſenting their
humble conſiderations, reaſons, and petitions to thoſe whom they have
choſen, (there being no other due and begall way wherein thoſe that are
aggrieved can find redreſſe<note n="*" place="margin">Declarat. 2. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.
1642. 1. part book Decl. p. 720</note>) but rather that you will be pleaſed
to give all incouragement therein: <hi>In aſſured hope whereof we ſhall
pray, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But the Citizens with their Certificate could not be permitted to
deliver it, but were with violence thruſt out of the Committee-Chamber, and a
Guard cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for to ſet them packing with a vengeance: and being below in
the Court of Requeſts, ſome of them deſired M. <hi>Nicolas Tew</hi>
audibly to read the Certificate to the whole company, that ſo all of them
might fully underſtand it; for which<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114264:19"/>action he was by the
ſaid Committee (without any authority at all then from the Houſe) committed
priſoner to the Serjeant at Armes, where to this day hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines; a moſt
unjuſt and illegall action, and tending to the utter deſtruction of the
greatly impoveriſhed man, by his often late and moſt illegall and unjuſt
vexatious impriſonments, firſt, by the Houſe of Lords to the Fleet,
ſecondly, he was moſt illegally by the preſent Lord Mayor of London,
fetched out of his ſhop and committed to New gate, for having had in his
cuſtody one of the Petitions promoted by the Citizens of London: and now
thirdly, moſt illegally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and the reſt of
his arbitrary and tyrannicall Committee, who had not the leaſt power either
by Law or from the Houſe ſo to doe it.</p>
            <p>And when the ſaid Committee riſe, the ſaid Citizens by M.
<hi>Denzill Hollis</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter
Earle,</hi> and reverend Sir <hi>Samuel Luke,</hi> with other of their right
worthy comrades, the planters of tyranny, injuſtice and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were
abuſed and called by ſome of them rogues, villains, ſeditious, factious
fellowes, and violent hands laid upon them, offering to beat and cane them, and
to draw their ſwords upon them, and haled and pulled ſome of them to make
them priſoners by the law of their owne will, and then the fore-mentioned
Members of the Houſe made a moſt falſe, unjuſt and untrue report the
next day unto the Houſe of the ſaid Citizens carriage, and particularly of
Major <hi>Tulidah,</hi> by meanes of which the Houſe of Commons outſtripped
the Pagan Judges of <hi>Paul</hi> in injuſtice, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.17. and
paſt a vote to commit or condemne Major <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidah</hi> to priſon,
without hearing or examining any witneſſes againſt him, or ſo much as
hearing him to ſpeake one word for himſelfe, although he waited then at the
door of purpoſe expecting to be called in to ſpeake for himſelfe, which
was not affoorded unto him, (his fore-mentioned adverſaries being both
Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Jurors and Judges) but without any more adoe clapt by the
heels.</p>
            <p>Which act of the Houſe of Commons is an act of ſo much
baſeneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, that the very Heathen and Pagan Romanes will
riſe up in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe imaginary pretended Chriſtians, who
by the ſingle light of nature were able to anſwer <hi>Pauls</hi>
adverſaries, when they would unjuſtly have had judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt him,
that it is not the manner (or Law) of the Romanes (then In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells, Pagans, and
Heathens,) to deliver any man to die, before that he which is accuſed, have
the accuſers face to face, and have licenſe to anſwer for himſelf
concerning the crime laid againſt him, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.17.</p>
            <p>But Major <hi>Tulidah</hi> being in priſon as well as M.
<hi>Nicholas Tue,</hi> their fore-ſaid friends and fellow-Citizens the next
day framed a Petition to the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Upon the reading of which Petition, M. <hi>Denzill Hollis,</hi>
and Sir <hi>Philip Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> knowing their owne guilt and how baſely
and unworthily they had abuſed<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114264:19"/>not onely the ſaid Major
<hi>Tulidah</hi> and his friends, but alſo the Houſe, in telling and
reporting unto them ſuch lies and falſhoods of them as they themſelves
had done, they themſelves being the truly guilty perſons, and knowing very
well that if Major <hi>Tulidah,</hi> &amp;c. had comed to the Bar, as both he
and his friends deſired, their baſeneſſe, lies, and falſhoods, would
have been laid open to their faces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole Houſe: to prevent which
they themſelves became and were the principall inſtruments at the hands of
the Houſe to get him his liberty, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though themſelves were the principall
inſtruments to get the Houſe to clap him by the heels, yea and have ſet
their agents and inſtruments alſo upon honeſt M. <hi>Tue,</hi> to get him
to frame a few lines by way of Petition to the Houſe for his liberty, which
he abſolutely refuſing, to this very day remaines in the meſſengers
hands a priſoner at Weſtminſter, to the apparent ruine and deſtruction
of the poore man, contrary to all Law and Juſtice, there being no colour of
law or juſtice for his firſt commitment, and as little law fot the
continuation of it; which clearly appeares by the Speakers arbitrary and
tyrannicall Warrant, which thus followeth.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="warrant">
                        <p>BY vertue of an Order of the Houſe of Commons, theſe
are to require you, that <hi>Nicholas Tue</hi> now in your cuſtody, be
continued in ſafe cuſtody untill the pleaſure of the Houſe be
ſignified to you to the contrary: And for ſo doing this ſhall be your
Warrant.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Dated <date>the 19. of March,
1646.</date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>
                              <hi>William Lenthall,</hi>
Speaker.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="appointment">
                        <p>To <hi>Edward Birkhead</hi> Eſquire, Serjeant and Armes
attending the Houſe of Commons.</p>
                        <p>I do nominate and appoint <hi>George Brag,</hi> and
<hi>Henry Radley,</hi> Gentlemen, to be my lawfull Deputies, for the due
execution of this Warrant, dated the 19. of March, 1646.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Edward Birkhead</hi> Serjeant at
Armes.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I pray Sir, be judge your ſelfe, whether this Warrant of M.
Speakers be not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely point-blank againſt the Law, <hi>(which you
have all ſworne to maintaine)</hi> and againſt the very words of the moſt
<hi>excellent Petition of right,</hi> made in the third yeare of the preſent
King, which expreſſely requires, <hi>that in all commitments, the cauſe
of the commitment ſhall be expreſſed,</hi> which is not in this, and ſo
poor M. <hi>Tue</hi> is deprived of his legall and hereditary priviledge, to
ſeek at Kings-Bench Barre, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for a <hi>habias corpus,</hi> and
the rather becauſe this tyrannicall warrant hath no legall concluſion as it
ought to have, <hi>viz. and him ſafely to keep untill he be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by due
courſe of Law,</hi> as Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> your owne learned Oracle of
the Law declares in his 2. <hi>part</hi> of Inſtitutes <hi>fol.</hi> 52.
which is printed by your own ſpecial order, and yet by your Houſe (or at
leaſt your Speaker) who ought to bee the Conſervators of the Law, and
ſevere puniſhers of the violators of it, poor M. <hi>Tue</hi> muſt be
without the leaſt ſhadow of cauſe disfranchiſed, ſpoyled and robbed
of<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114264:20"/>the benefit of the Law, and muſt by your wills remaine
in priſon till it be the pleaſure of your Houſe to do juſtice, which I
am confident in the way you goe, and have lately gone, muſt be till
doomes-day in the afternoone, for I am ſure, you have loſt the very
ſoule, eſſence, and being of true Magiſtracie, which is to doe
<hi>juſtice, judgement, and right, and to relieve the afflicted, the
helpleſſe, fatherleſſe, and widdow, and to let the oppreſsed goe
free;</hi> and are I will maintaine, degene ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the notoriouſeſt
packe of Tyrants that ever in the world were aſſembled together ſince
<hi>Adams</hi> creation, that profeſſed Humanity, Morality, and
Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, minding viſibly nothing in the world, but pleaſure,
oppreſſion, tyranny, cheating and couzening the whole Kingdome of its
treaſure and revenue, trades, lives, bloods, liberties, and properties; for
which (I proteſt before the Almighty God) in my judgement, you deſerve
nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t to be pulled out by the
eares, and throwne out to the dunghill, and be trodden under-foot by all men
that have but the leaſt ſparks of juſtice, honor, conſcience or
honeſty in them, &amp; I profeſs I cannot fully acquit one man of you that
ſits there, being all of you (in the eye of both law and reaſon)
Acceſſaries unto the Principals, by your baſe, ſilent, tame and patient
ſitting there, and not proteſting againſt their Actions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly
and publikely to the whole Kingdome, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.58. compared with Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
8.1, &amp; Ch. 22.24. where <hi>Paul</hi> poſitively accuſeth himſelfe,
<hi>for being guilty of the murder and blood of righteous</hi> Stephen,
<hi>although wee read not that he either was an actor in throwing him out of
the City, or ſtoning him, but only that he ſtood by and ſee it, but
declared nothing againſt it;</hi> therefore ſay I to you, partake not with
them in their evills by continuing with them, but be divided from them, leaſt
you partake of their plagues, which muſt unavoidably, ſpeedily, and
powerfully come upon them, to their tranſcendent and exemplary deſtruction,
if God be (as undoubtedly he is) a God of righteouſneſſe, juſtice, and
truth.</p>
            <p>But now Sir, ſeeing that to maintaine the good Lawes of the Land
and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh the bad ones, and to redreſſe the miſchiefs and
grievances that daily hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3.14. &amp; 36. <hi>E.</hi> 3.10.
ſee <hi>The reſolved mans Reſolution, pag.</hi> 19. are the maine and
principal ends wherefore Parliaments are called, and being it is
impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for you the peoples choſen and betruſted Stewards or
Commiſſioners to know the grievances of the people, your Empowerers,
earthly Creators, Lord and Maſters, if you take away the liberty of declaring
them unto you, which you have done, let me a little demonſtrate, whether or
no that you, by your late burn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing their Petitions <hi>&amp;c.</hi> refuſing
to hear their grievances, have not poſitively an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> viſibly declared that you have forfeited your
eſſence and being, &amp; abſolutely nul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lified the end of your ſitting,
and are from a company of faithfull and careful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Shepheards, appointed to preſerve the being and well-being of
this poore Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon-wealth, become to be a company of devouring Lions and
ravening Wolves <pb n="39" facs="tcp:114264:20"/>who deſerve to have all the Maſtie
Doggs in the Kingdome let looſe about your eares, to worry and pull you in
pieces, and ſo deſtroy you, before you have total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waſted and
deſtroyed this poore Kingdome, already in the hie rode way to be deſtroyed
by you.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the Citizens Petitions to your Houſe, after
they had been ſo ſleighted about their Certificate, by the aforeſaid
Committee, and ſo abuſed by M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip
Stapleton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Walter Earle,</hi> that baſe coward, that ran
away, betrayed, or at leaſt in a ground leſſe pannick feare, deſerted
Dorcheſter in Dorſetſhire, when it was well and plentifully provided with
Ammunition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and alſo ſo behaved himſelfe at
Corfe-Caſtle, that he deſerves to bee ſtiled the chiefe of baſe,
unworthy, and cowardly men; and after that M. <hi>Nicholas Tue,</hi> and Major
<hi>Tuliday,</hi> was (as is before declared) moſt unjuſtly impriſoned,
the ſaid honeſt Citizens preſented the Houſe with a Petition, which
thus followeth:</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Right Honourrable, the COMMONS of ENGLAND
aſſembled in PARLIAMENT. The humble Petition of divers well-affected
Citizens.</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat as the oppreſſions of this Nation, in times
fore-going this Parliament were ſo numerous and burthen ſome, as will never
be forgotten; ſo were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he hopes
of our deliverance by this Parliament, exceding great and full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,
which as they were ſtrenthned by many Acts of yours in the begining,
ſpecially towards conſciencious people, without reſpect unto their
judgments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r opinions; So did the
gratitude of well-minded people exceed all preſident or
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xample, ſparing neither
eſtates, limbs, liberties, or lives, to make good the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hourity of this Honorable Houſe, as
the foundation and root of all juſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ome.</p>
                        <p>And although we many times obſerved to our grief, ſome
proceedings holding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſemblance
rather with our former bondage, then with that juſt freedome we
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xpected: yet did we impute the
ſame to the troubleſomeneſſe of the times of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ar, patiently and ſilently
paſſing them over, as undoubtedly hopeing a perfect
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>medy ſo ſoon as the warres
were ended: but perceiving our expectations alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ether fruſtrate, we conceived our ſelves bound in
conſcience, and in duty to God, <pb n="40" facs="tcp:114264:21"/>to ſet before you the
generall grievances of the Common-wealth, and the earneſt deſires of
ingenuous well-minded people: and for that did ingage in promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the
Petition in queſtion, in the uſuall and approved way of gathering
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, with full intention to preſent the ſame to this
Honourable Houſe ſo ſoon as it ſhould be in readineſſe: but as it
appeareth, a Copy thereof was unduly obtained, and tendred to this Honourable
Houſe under the notion of a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſeditious Paper: Whereupon this
Houſe was pleaſed to order the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the Committee, whereof Col.
<hi>Lee</hi> is Chairman; and Mr. <hi>Lambe</hi> at whoſe Houſe it was
ſaid to be found, to be there examined concerning the ſame.</p>
                        <p>Whereupon your Petitioners conceived it their duty to own
and avouch the ſaid Petition, &amp; for that end, in a peaceable manner
attended that Committee with this humble Certificate herunto annexed, to be
offered ro their wiſdomes as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por tunity ſhould be miniſtred: but
through ſome ſmall miſcarriage of ſome few perſons (for which your
Petitioners were much grieved) your Committee took ſo ſuddain and high
diſpleaſure, as to command your Petioners to withdraw threatning to remove
them with a guard, before they had time to turn themſelves.</p>
                        <p>Whereupon your Petitioners cauſed the Certificate to be
publikely read in the Court of Requeſts, to take the ſence and allowance of
many perſons who had not before ſeen the ſame, with intent ſtill to
preſent it; which though endeavoured to be utmoſt, was abſolutely
refuſed to be received, but to our aſtoniſhment, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion was taken
againſt our friend M. <hi>Nicholas Tue</hi> that read the ſame, ſo far,
as that he ſtands a priſoner to that Committee, and much harſh language,
with threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and provocations iſſued from ſome of the Committee,
towards ſome other of our friends purpoſely (as we verily beleeve) to get
ſome advantage, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent us odious to this Honorable Houſe, whoſe
perſons and authority hath been as deare in our eſteeme as our very lives.
And therefore, wee have juſt cauſe to complaine to this Honorable
Houſe,</p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Of unjuſt uſage from thoſe that endeavoured
to interrupt the gathering of hands in a peaceable way, or to poſſeſſe
this Honorable Houſe with evill ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions concerning the intention and
purpoſe of the ſaid Petition.</item>
                           <item>2. Of hard meaſure from your Committee in the
particulars fore-mentioned contrary to what we have deſerved, or ſhould
have found in former times.</item>
                           <item>3. Nevertheleſſe, our liberties, to promote
Petitions to this Honorable Houſe is ſo eſſentiall to our freedome,
(out condition without the ſame being abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſlavery) and our hope of
juſtice from this Honorable Houſe, is ſo eſſential<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> to our freedome, our condition,
without the ſame being abſolute ſlavery: And our hope of juſtice from
this Honorable Houſe ſo great, in protecting us therein that we are not
diſcouraged by what hath paſſed, but in confidence thereof, do humbly
intreat, 
<list>
                                 <pb n="41" facs="tcp:114264:21"/>
                                 <item>Firſt, <hi>That ye will be pleaſed to declare
our freedome, to promote, and your readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to receive the ſaid
Petition, which we cannot but ſtill looke upon, as tending to the generall
good of this Nation.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Secondly, <hi>That our friends may be inlarged
and that Ye will diſcountenance the officiouſneſſe of ſuch
over-buſie informers, as have diſturbed the iuſt progreſſe of that
Petition.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>We are not ignorant, that we have been, and are like to be
repreſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, as Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, Sectaries, ſeditious
perſons, and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Civill-government, and the like: but our ſaid
Petition is ſufficient to ſtop the mouthes of ſuch calumniators, and
declare us to be not only ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for our own particulars, but for the
generall good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and will miniſter a juſt occaſion to
ſuſpect the deſignes of thoſe, that ſo frequently aſperſe us,
though their pretences be never ſo ſpecious. And we truſt your
wiſedomes will timeouſly diſcover and prevent any evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
againſt us.</p>
                        <p>And whereas Major <hi>Tuledah</hi> ſtands committed by
Order of this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe, for ſome conceived misbehaviour towards
ſome Members of your ſaid Committee; we humbly intreat, that he may be
forthwith called to your Barre, and be permitted to anſwer for himſelfe,
and that witneſſes may be alſo heard on his behalfe, which juſtice
could never yet be obtained, that ſo this honourable Houſe may be rightly
and fully informed, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his cauſe and demeanour of thoſe Members,
the ſuddain impriſonment of our friends
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eing very grievous unto us.</p>
                        <closer>And your Petitioners ſhall pray.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The ſpecified certificate you will read before in pag. 35.</p>
            <p>But finding no benefit to themſelves by this Petition, although
they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it extraordinary cloſe, and at the doote preſented it to all
the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in print, and therefore imediately upon it they frame another, and
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got a competent number of hands to it, they preſented it in writing,
And afterwards in print, to all the Members that would receive it, the true
copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE COMMONS OF ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
aſſembled in Parliament. The Humble <hi>Petition</hi> of divers well
affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted people in and about the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat as the Authority of this Honourable Houſe is
intruſted by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for remedie of their grievances, ſo hath it been
their uncuſtomed and undoubted liberty in a peaceable manner to preſent
unto this Houſe what<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114264:22"/>ſoever they deemed to be particular
or generall grievances: And as ye gave encouragement unto others in the uſe
of this juſt Liberty, reproving ſuch as endeavour to obſtruct the
peaceable promoting of Petitions, ſo did we veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope to have found the
like countenance and protection in promoting our large Petition: but no
ſooner was the promoting thereof diſcovered, but Mr. <hi>Glin</hi> Recorder
as is commonly reported, haſtily and untimely brought it into the Houſe,
exclaiming againſt it, as a moſt dangerous and ſedition, paper, and
ſhortly after the Common Counſel in like manner prejudged it, as guilty of
danger and ſedition, though both without any grounds or reaſons affixed,
that we know of.</p>
                        <p>And as the worke of Mr. Recorder was the occaſion (as we
conceive) of an inquiry after the promoters, ſo alſo of the hard meaſure
we found at Col. <hi>Lieghs</hi> Committee, where occaſion was ſuddenly
taken to threatten or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move by guard, to imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iſon <hi>Nicholas Tew,</hi> one of the Petitioners, the reſt
being reviled with odious titles of factious and ſeditious Sectaries and
Major <hi>Tulidah</hi> another of the Petitioners, not only reviled and
reproached as the reſt, but violently hauled, and moſt boyſterouſly
uſed by Sir <hi>Philip, Stapleton,</hi> and Col. <hi>Hollis,</hi> who made
offer as if they would draw their Swords upon the Petitioners, and Sir
<hi>Walter Earle</hi> lifting up his Caen in a moſt threatning manner, took
another by the ſhoulder: all which is ready to be certified by ſufficient
witneſſes, and which we doe verily beleeve was done purpoſely, out of
their hatred to the matter of the Petition, to render us as a turbulent people
to this Honourable Houſe, to begit a miſlike of our Petition, and to
fruſtrate our endeavours in promoting thereof.</p>
                        <p>Unto which their miſinformation of this honourable
houſe, as we have cauſe to ſuſpect, may be imputed the occaſion of
the ſudden impriſonment of Major <hi>Tulidah</hi> without heating of him,
and our ſo long and tedious atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance for anſwer to our laſt Petition
and Certificate, and the miſapprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this honourable houſe of our
deſires in that Petition: For we did not deſire (as your anſwer
importeth) that this houſe ſhould declare their liking or diſliking of
our large Petition, being not then promoted nor preſented by us, but that you
will be pleaſed to vindicate our Liberty, to promote that Petition,
notwithſtanding the hard meaſure we had found, and the aſperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons caſt
upon it, to releaſe the party impriſoned by the Committee, meaning
<hi>Nicholas Tew,</hi> to diſcountenance thoſe that obſtructed the
gathering of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, to call Major <hi>Tulidah</hi> to your Bar,
and to heare witneſſes on his behalfe, that ſo he might be alſo rightly
informed, as of his cauſe, ſo of the demeanor of ſome members of that
Committee.</p>
                        <p>Now for as much as the more we conſider the generall
grievances of the<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114264:22"/>Common wealth, the greater cauſe we
ſtill find of promoting of the large Petition, as not diſcerning any thing
of danger therein<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> except in ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions yet remaining, nor of
ſedition, except as before this Parliament it be in ſome mens eſteemes
ſeditious to move, though in the moſt peaceably manner for remedy of the
moſt palpable grievances; and for as much as we are hopefull this Honourable
Houſe will in due time have good uſe thereof, for the diſcovery of ſuch
as are ingaged either directly or by Relations in thoſe corruptions, for
removall whereof the Petition is intended, and not knowing for what end ſo
great an effuſion of the blood of the people hath been made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> except to
procure at the leaſt the particulars deſired in that Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that we
might know our ſelves ſo farre at leaſt to be free men and not ſlaves,
as to be at liberty to promote Petitions in a peaceable way, to be Iudges of
the matter thereof, and for our time of preſenting them to this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
Houſe, without let or circumvention.</p>
                        <p>We humbly intreat that ye will be pleaſed</p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. To weigh in equall Ballance the carriage of Mr.
Recorder, and that of the Common Counſell in this weighty cauſe of
prejudging Petitions, and to deale with them as the cauſe deſerveth.</item>
                           <item>2. To conſider of how evill conſequence it is,
for your Committees to to aſſume a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>wer of impriſoning mens perſons, without your Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
and that ye will not paſſe over this in this Committee.</item>
                           <item>3. To receive the Teſtimonies concerning Sir
<hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Col. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Walier Earle,</hi>
and to deale with them according to the ill conſequences of their violent
demeanour, and miſinformation of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe, tending to no
leſſe then the obſtruction of Petitions the gleateſt miſchiefe that
can befall a people in time of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                           <item>4. That <hi>Nicholas Tew</hi> may be wholly inlarged,
and that no man may hence forth be committed by an Arbitrary power, as he at
the firſt was, nor without cauſe ſhewed, though by lawfull
Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</item>
                           <item>5. That ye will as yet ſuſpend your ſenſe of
our Large Petition, untill ſuch time as the Petitioners ſhall judge it fit
to preſent the ſame as a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto your wiſedomes.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>And as in duty bound we ſhall pray,
&amp;c.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But this Petition being againſt Mr. <hi>Hellis,</hi> and Sir
<hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> the Captains and heads of the ſubverters of our
Lawes, liberties, and freedomes, after it was debated, it was, as your Diurnall
tells me, upon the 20 of <hi>May,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:114264:23"/>1647
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oted, 1. <hi>To be a high breach
of Priviledges.</hi> 2. <hi>That it was ſeditious.</hi> 3. <hi>That this
Petition and the former, intituled, The humble Petition of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anas, &amp;c. ſhould be burnt at the
Exchange in Cornewell, and the Pallace yard at Weſtminſter, Saterday
next.</hi> Which as I am informed was accordingly done, by the hands of the
common hang-man.</p>
            <p>Vpon which the petitioners not being willing to be bafled out of
their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties in making known their grievances; (without the injoyment of
which they are perfect 
<note n="*" place="margin">Read your owne words, in Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. <hi>720.</hi>
               </note> ſlaves) they reſolve to attempt a
Petition once more, though divers of them
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather deſired to remonſtrate
againſt you to the whole Kingdome, for a company of tyrannicall deſtroyers,
and treacherous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers (contrary to your oaths, and the duty of your
places) of the Lawes, Liberties, and Freedomes of England And having
diſcourſed my ſelfe with ſome of them, and perceiving they were
reſolved to petition once again, I told them I conceived they had nothing
elſe to petition for, as things at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtood with your houſe, but
theſe two things, viz. <hi>That ſeeing the Houſe had voted they had
broken their priviledges, by petitioning unto them for redreſſe of their
grievances, without declaring wherein,</hi> how<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or after what manner, or
giving any reaſons at all, wherefore they burnt their honeſt Petition,
<hi>that therefore they would be pleaſed forthwith, publiquely and
diſtinctly to declare unto the whole Kingdome, what their priviledges are,
and when, how and after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they came by them, that ſo in future
time through ignorance, in not knowing their priviledges, they might not run
upon the pricks of their iudignation, and the Hang-Mans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>That they would alſo be pleaſed to declare and dictate
to them, what, (how and after what manner) they ſhould petition for; the next
time they would vouchſafe to give them leave to Petition to them, that ſo
their Petition might not againe be burnt by the hands of the common Hang-man;
and I withall told them the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons anſwer to their laſt
Petition, did neceſſarily and iuſtly lead them as it were by the
hand,</hi> to ſuch a petition as this; but they rejected it, and framed one
of their owne, the Copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Right Honourable the Commons of <hi>England</hi>
Aſſembled in Parliament. The humble <hi>Petition</hi> of many thouſands
of well affected People.</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth:</opener>
                        <p>THat having ſeriouſly conſidered what an
uncontrouled liberty hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally been taken, publiquely to reproach, and
make odious perſons of eminent and conſtant good affection to Parliament
and common wealth,<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114264:23"/>how prevalent indeavours have been, to
withhold ſuch from being choſen into places of truſt or Counſell, how
eaſie to moleſt, or get them into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, how exceedingly liable to
miſconſtruction, their motions and Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in behalfe of the publique
have lately been.</p>
                        <p>When we conſider what grudgings and repinings, have
ſiniſtrouſly been b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gotten,
againſt your moſt faithfull and ſucceſſefull Army: what arts and
deviſes, to prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke you againſt
them and to make y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lous of them; what hard meaſure
ſome of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m, both Offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rs and
Soldiers have found in divers reſpects in ſundry places?</p>
                        <p>When we conſider, what change of late hath importunately
(th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ugh cauſſeſſely) been
procured of the Committee of Militia in the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and how
that new Committee hath already begun to remove from Command, in the Train'd
bands and Auxiliaries, perſons not to be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>affection or
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ewerality but ſuch as have been
moſt zealous, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the ſafety of Parliament and City.</p>
                        <p>When we conſider how full of Armies our neighbour
Countries are round about us, and what threatning of forrain forces, wee are
even aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with griefe as not able to free our ſelves from
apprehenſion of eminent danger, but are ſtrongly induced to feare ſome
evill intentions of ſome deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and wilfull perſons, yet powerfully
working to blaſt the juſt ends of this Parliament, and re-imbroile this
late bleeding and much waſted Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in more violent warres, diſtempers
and miſeries.</p>
                        <p>And as our earneſt deſires of the quiet and ſafety
of the Common wealth, hath neceſſitated theſe our moſt ſad
obſervations: So are we conſtrained to beleeve, that ſo dangerous an
alteration, could not ſo generally have appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but that there is ſome
great alteration befaln, both in Counſels and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities throughout the
land; which we verily conceive ariſeth from no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, but from the
treacherous policie of enemies, and weakneſſe of friends, in chuſing
ſuch thereinto, as have been unfit for thoſe imployments, ſome whereof
(as is credibly reported) having ſerved the enemie in Armes, ſome with
moneys, horſe, ammunition, or by intelligence, ſome in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of
Array, ſome manifeſting conſtant malignity in their actions, ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
or ſtanding Newters in times of greateſt tryall, ſome culpable of
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious crimes; others lying under heavie accuſations, ſome that are
under age, or ſuch who are at preſent ingaged in ſuch courſes as in the
beginning of this Parliament were eſteemed Monopolies.</p>
                        <p>Now may it pleaſe this honourable Houſe, if ſuch as
theſe ſhould remain, or may have privily crept into our Counſells or
Authorities (as by the forecited conſiderations, we humbly conceive cannot
but be judged) what<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114264:24"/>can poſſibly be expected, by thoſe
who have been moſt active and faithfull in your ſervi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> but utter ruine or the worſt of bondage.</p>
                        <p>For prevention whereof, and of thoſe dangers, warres and
troubles that are genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>y feared:
we are conſtrained earneſtly to intreat.</p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. That you will be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>eaſed inſtantly to appoint a Committee of ſuch worthy members
of this honourable H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>uſe, as have
manifeſted moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affections, to the well affected, and to
authorize them to make ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>ict inquir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e after all ſuch as are poſſeſſed of places of
Counſell, truſt, auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rity or
command, who according to law, Ordinances, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ty, ought not to be admitted: and that all perſons without
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception may be permitted and incouraged, to bring in accuſations,
wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, or teſtimonies for the more ſpeedy perfecting of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ke: and that you will forthwith exclude
all ſuch out of all offices of counſell, truſt Authority or command,
againſt whom ſufficient cauſe ſhall be proved, without which we cannot
ſee how it is poſſible for the well affected to live either in peace or
ſafety.</item>
                           <item>2. That you will countenance, protect, and ſuccour
the cordiall well affected in all places, according to their ſeverall caſes
and conditions, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in their addreſſes with petitions.</item>
                           <item>3. That you will be pleaſed to condiſcend unto
all the juſt and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>es of your Commanders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Officers, and Soldiers, by whoſe
cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and faithfulneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo great ſervices have been performed,
and ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to puniſh all ſuch as have any way ſought to alienate you
from them.</item>
                           <item>4. That the Militia, of <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ndon</hi> may be returned to the cuſtody and
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of thoſe perſons of whoſe faithfullneſſe and
wiſedome in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thereof, you have had great experience, and that none
may be put out of Command in the Trained Bands, or Auxiliaries, who have been
and are of known good affection to the Common wealth.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>All which we humbly intreat may be ſpeedily and
effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually accompliſhed, according to the great neceſſity and exigency
of theſe diſtracted times, and as in duty bound, we ſhall pray,
&amp;c.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And having preſented it in writing, a day, two or three after
they preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it publiquely in print to the members of the Houſe, the
iſſue of which as I have it out of your own Diurnall was thus.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Mercuris 2 Junii.
1647</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>A Petition ſtiled, the humble Petition of many
thouſands of well affected people, was this day read.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="47" facs="tcp:114264:24"/>The queſtion being put, whether an
anſwer ſhall be given to this Petition at this preſent, the houſe was
devided the yeas went forth</p>
                        <p>Sir John Evelin of Wilts, Sir Michael Leviſay tellers
for the yea, with the yea, <hi>112.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Hollis, Sir William Luis, tellers for the no, with the
no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s <hi>128</hi> ſo that the
qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtion paſt with the
negative.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But the Petitioners going up ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me few dayes after for an anſwer to their petition, and being
extreamly in baſe provoking and inſufferable language abuſed by that
worſhipfull Gentleman, Major Generall <hi>Maſſie,</hi> &amp;c. which
provoked divers of them to ſend in a paper to Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi> as their
laſt fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, the copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr Speaker, divers Citizens have been here attending for an
anſwer of a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on delivered by Sir William Waller on Wedneſday laſt,
their deſire is that the houſe may be acquainted</hi> that the petitioners
have ſeen the Vote of the Houſe, and have diſcharged themſelves from
further attendance for the preſent, and will notwithſtanding ſtill
ſeeke juſt and equitable meanes for to eaſe the grievances of this poore
diſtracted Kingdome, and comfortably put an end to the groanings of this
miſerable diſtreſſed nation.</p>
            <p>And having ſent it in, away they came, and now in my
apprehenſion have no other courſe to take, but to remonſtrate and
juſtly to declare to all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> and the Army, the
unpartaleld, illegall and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall dealing of the Houſe of Commons with
them, and to preſſe them by force of Armes to root up and deſtroy theſe
tyrants, which without any ſcruple of conſcience they may doe, if it were
lawfull for the two Houſes to levie warre againſt the King for tyranny
declared by them, ſeeing I am ſure there is a hundred times greater and
more viſibler, and if it be true as Sir <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Synod,</hi> and the
<hi>John</hi> of all Sir <hi>Johns</hi> now cryes out and ſayes that it is
not lawfull in any caſe to fight againſt the legall Magiſtrate, then I am
ſure Sir <hi>John</hi> and Sir <hi>Simon</hi> are a company of grand
Traytors, and ought principally to be hanged, for being the chiefe Incendiaries
in their Pulpets, &amp;c. to the by paſt warres againſt the King, who I
will juſtifie it upon the loſſe of my life, by the eſtabliſhed law of
<hi>England,</hi> the declared government thereof, is a thouſand times more
fenced about and ſecured, (ſo farre as Law can ſecure) then the unjuſt,
law and liberty deſtroying Lords and Commons aſſembled at
<hi>Weſtminſter</hi> are.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, I will juſtifie it, that if the principalls, or
law of reaſon and nature for preſervation take be a ſufficient ground to
take up Armes againſt the King and his party as the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Parliament have declared they are, then the Kingdome
and Arm, have much more true grounds to take up<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114264:25"/>Armes
againſt them for tyranny viſibly, avowedly, and profeſſedly acted, a
hundred times more higher and tranſendent then ever he did, that is yet
declared. And a moſt reall difference there is betwixt the action of them two
in this particular.</p>
            <p>I clearly find by all that J can yet read of either ſide,
publiſhed to the view of the Kingdome, (and J thinke that I have read and
wayed almoſt all that is extant) that the King by the law of his will did not
impoſe Monopolies and Ship money, &amp;c. vpon the free men of
<hi>England,</hi> but was made to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve by his Judges and Counſell at Law,
(being thoſe helpes or aſſiſtance that the law of the Kingdom had
appointed him to be counſelled by out of Parliament) that he might impoſe
thoſe things by right, or force of the Law of the Kingdome. See the diſpute
in Mr. <hi>Hamdens</hi> caſe of Ship-money, in the latter end of Judge
<hi>Huttons</hi> Judge <hi>Crookes</hi> arguments againſt Ship mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, pag. 2
3. 4, 5 printed by authority of this preſent Parliament, and the Declarations
of both ſides, 1. and 2. part Col. Decl. And indeed to ſpeake according to
the declared Law of England, the Iudges and his counſell at Law were
principally to be blamed, and not the King. See your own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of the
19 <hi>May,</hi> 1642. 1. part book Decl. pag. 199. 304. and the reaſon in
Law is becauſe, 
<q rend="inline">"the Law commands the Judges and Juſtices of
peace, and all the reſt of the Adminiſtrators of it, not to delay or
diſturb common Iuſtice and right, for any command from the King, for any
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſignified by the Great Seale, or privie Seale, or any other wayes,
and though ſuch commands doe come the Iudges and Iuſtices ſhall not
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leave to doe right in any point, but ſhall doe common right,
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common Law, as though never any ſuch command had been,
ſee the 29 chap of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and 2. <hi>E.</hi> 3 8. and 14.
<hi>E.</hi> 3.14. and 11. <hi>R.</hi> 2.10</q> And to performe this in every
particular, every Iudge and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of peace is ſworne, as appeares by
their oathes recorded in <hi>Poultons book of Statutes,</hi> folio 144. and
made in the 18. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> 3. <hi>Anno;</hi> 1344. which alſo
you may verbatum read, in the 29: pag. of a late printed book called
<hi>Rega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tyranny.</hi> And it was
the duty by law that this Parliament ought to the whole Kingdome, to have made
all thoſe falſe and wicked Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Judges examples of terror to future
generations. (As King <hi>Alfred</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the conqueſt did for as
<hi>Andrew Horne</hi> in his miror of Iuſtice pag. 296. ſaith, 
<q rend="inline">"that Iudges and their Miniſters who deſtroy
men by falſe judgement, ought to be deſtroyed as other murtherers, which
King <hi>Alfred</hi> did, who hanged in one yeare 44.</q> Iudges as murtherers,
for their falſe judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments
againſt the Law, whoſe particular crimes and names he ſpecifieth pag.
296. 297 298 299 300. &amp;c. But to your everlaſting ſhame be it ſpoken,
you<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114264:25"/>took bribes of ſome of them, after the King had
ſurrendred them up to your juſtice, and after that you had impeached them
of high Treaſon, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned them, you ſet them at liberty to ſit
upon the ſeat of juſtice 
<note n="*" place="margin">Which if they had bin made examples of
terror you would have got no Iudges to have executed your arbitrary, illegall
and tirannicall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</note> to paſſe ſentence upon the lives,
liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and properties of the free-men of <hi>England,</hi> and if I
miſtake not, one of them continues a Judge in your Commiſſion to this
very day, by meanes of which baſe and wicked practiſes of yours, (I meane
the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) this poore Kingdome under the pretence of Law, hath bin by
you fild <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi rend="sup">th</hi> more oppreſſion
&amp; injuſtice, then ever it underwent in ſo ſhort a time ſince the
<hi>Norman Conqueſt,</hi> there being neither pure Iuſtice nor Right to be
had according to law at the hands, either of your Iudges or Iuſtices of
peace, being in every particular as corrupt as either the Houſe of Lords or
Commons, <hi>Tyburne,</hi> or at leaſt to row at Oares as ſlaves, being the
fitteſt portion for the moſt part of them, there being never ſuch
out-cryes in the Kings time againſt has Judges and Juſtices, as you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s denying dayly the benefit of
<hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Petition of Right, to any free-man that a
knaviſh Parliament man appears againſt; as I could eaſily enumerate
divers inſtances if it were ſeaſonable, but I will keep it in banke for a
repreſentation for the Army or the next Parliament, where I hope they will
take ſpeciall care, what ever they doe with the preſent baſe Judges and
Iuſtices of peace; to provide an act of Parliament, that we may have our
lawes (where they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ambigues and
doubtfull) made as plaine as can be made, and all our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in law in
Engliſh, briefe and ſhort, in plain Engliſh words, and quick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to be diſcided. And that it ſhall
be treaſon in any Iudge, or Iuſtices, by vertue of any command
whatſoever, to pervert the Common law, and the Common Iuſtice of the
Kingdome, and without ſuch a law, and an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Parliament to ſee it
executed, the conſtitution of which in point of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, had extraordinary
need to be amended, for now ſome Counties chuſing about 50. As
<hi>Cornewell</hi> and others none, as the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> and their
corporations many times made by bribes given to corrupt Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, to obtaine
the Kings Letters, patents, <hi>(which meerly flowes from his will)</hi> to
inable them to chuſe two Burgeſſes for Parliament, in divers of which
petty and paultery Corporations throughout the Kingdome, any baſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
for 20. or 30 I may by ſo many voices as will make him a Burgeſſe of
Parliament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and divers of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe corporations, conſiſting for a great part of Inns and Ale
houſes, will be ſure to chuſe no other Parliament men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but ſuch as
are given to depoſedneſſe, expenſiveneſſe, wickedneſſe, and
drinking, or at leaſt ſome Ninnie and Groſe, wrictor by a great man, that
as Dr. <hi>Baſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:114264:26"/>ſaith, hath no more wit in
him, then will reach from his noſe to his mouth. And this is the true
reaſon why our Parliament men in all ages have ſo little regard to the
Common and iuſt liberties of the Kingdome, or to the iuſtice and equity of
the lawes they make. And therefore as I ſaid in the 54. pag. of <hi>Londons
Liberties,</hi> ſo I ſay now to you, that it would be more rationall
<hi>and a great deale fuller of juſtice and equity, to deſtroy all theſe
illegall Corporations, and fix upon them the certain number of Parliament men,
be they</hi> 600. 500. or 400. <hi>or more or leſſe, as by the common
conſent ſhall be thought moſt fit, and equally to proportion to every
Country, to chuſe a proportionable number, ſutable to the rates, that each
County by their bookes of rates, are aſſeſſed to pay towards the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraying of the publique charge of the Kingdome, and then each County equally
and proportionably, by the common conſent of the people thereof,</hi> to
divide it ſelfe into Diviſions, Hundreds, or Weapontacks, that ſo all the
people (without confuſion or tumult) may meet together in their ſeverall
diviſions, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry free man of <hi>England,</hi> as well poore as rich,
whoſe life eſtate &amp;c. is to be taken away by the law, may have a Vote
in chuſing thoſe that are to make the law, it being a maxim in nature, that
no man iuſtly can be bound with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his own conſent, and care taken that
this may be once every yeare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faile, and to hold for a certain number
of dayes, without which this Kingdome will never be free from warres, miſery
and commotions; but from this preſent Parliament, I neither looke for good to
my particular ſelfe, or the Kingdome in generall, the conſtant and
uninterrupted ſerious of all your viſible actions, being a viſible and
cleare demonſtartion to the eyes of every unbioſed, impartiall and
rationall man in <hi>England,</hi> of an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute violation of the lawes and
liberties of <hi>England,</hi> and ſetting up a perfect tyranny, declaring
thereby both in the ſight of God and man, that you have ſold, and given up
your ſelves to worke and act all manner of wickedneſſe and impietie,
<hi>admitting no other rule either of reaſon, law, or juſtice, to ſquare
your actions by, but your own perverſe and crooked wills, being an abſolute
kind of monſters of the Divells, but not of Gods creation, who never made any
man lawleſſe</hi> as you avowedly profeſſe your ſelves to be, robbing
and poling the poore Kingdome by all manner of illegall taxations, Exciſe,
&amp;c. and then ſharing it amongſt your ſelves, making nothing of fifty
thouſand pounds at one breakfaſt in one morning, for ten of your owne
Members, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr <hi>Denzel Hollis.</hi> Mr <hi>Walter Long,</hi>
&amp;c. and for all your Hypocriticall, cheating, and ſelfe denying
Ordinance, within a little while after, (as I am informed) in ſtate Mr.
<hi>Long</hi> (as I am told) worth five thouſand pounds per Annum, <hi>viz.
the Regiſter of the Chancery,</hi> and make the two Speakers, (both of whom
have been impeched if not of treaſon, yet of high miſdemeanors, &amp; were
never yet iuſtly<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114264:26"/>cleared and acquitted) keepers of the
great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> to raiſe up their juſtly loſt repute
with the people, thereby declaring that it is your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and delight, to
make uſe of the corrupteſt and baſeſt of men amongſt you, to
tyrannize over the people, and yet the worſt amongſt you are ſo pure and
holy, that you muſt not be touched, queſtioned, or called to an account for
any thing that you ſay or doe, ſo that your pretence to all our liberties,
eſtates, trades proprieties and lives, is not the law of the kingdome, 
<note n="*" place="margin">For Col. Burch a Member of the Houſe of
Commons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another Member and the Lieutenant of the Tower, did aver
before them the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day to iudge Ienkins when he queſtioned the lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of their proceedings, that they did not ſtand upon the Law, nor warrant their
actions thereby, but ſaith he we have conquered you by the Sword, and by the
Sword we will hold it. Therefore looke about you Free men of England, give the
Tyrants their deſerts.</note>but your owne inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent corrupt luſts, and
unbounded wills, ſo that the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fference betwixt you and the King is viſible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and that we
have got by our exchange of our former government for your tirannicall
domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, for I never read not heard that the King in the worſt of his
raign, within it ſelfe ſimply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, was I thinke bad enough and
not to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and which I my ſelfe felt as much as any man in
<hi>England,</hi> (yet compared to yours was glorious and beautifull) for did
he ever cauſe to be burnt by the hands of the Common hangman, the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of thoſe that he by his Declarations had invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Petition to him, and who
in his greateſt ſtraites, had been moſt hazardous for him, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
and firmiſt to him, both of which you have done, as is before proved. Neither
in the ſecond place, did I ever read that he did proclame and declare ſuch
men to be Rebells and Traitors, but for going about to make their juſt and
preſſing grievances knowne, which you have done to the Army, (yea, to
ſuch an Army, as I thinke I may iuſtly ſay in every particular the world
never had any) as may larger appeare by their Petition, and your declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
which as it is printed by themſelves, or ſome of their friends, thus
followeth.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>The Armies Petition. TO HIS EXCELLENCY SIR THOMAS
<hi>Fairfax,</hi> Generall for the Parliaments Forces The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition of
the Officers and Soldiers of the Army under your Command.</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat ever ſince our firſt ingagement in the ſervice
for the preſerving the power of this Kingdome in the hands of the Parliament,
we have in<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114264:27"/>out ſeverall places ſerved them with all
faithfullneſſe, and although we have laine under many diſcouragements,
for want of pay and other neceſſaryes, yet have we not diſputed their
commands, diſobeyed their Orders, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed them with petitions, nor
have there any viſible diſcontents appeared amongſt us, to the
incouragement of the enemie, and the impediment of their affaires, but have
with all cheerfullneſſe done Summer ſervice in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeaſons,
improving the utmoſt of our abillities, in the advancement of their
ſervice, and ſeeing God hath now crowned our indeavours with the end of our
deſire (<hi>viz.</hi> the diſpercing of the pulique Enemie, and reducing
them to their obedience) the King being now brought in, our brethren the
<hi>Scots</hi> now ſatisfied and departed the Kingdome, all danger
ſeemingly blown over, and peace in all their quarters.</p>
                        <p>We (imboldned by the many fold promiſes and Declarations
to defend and protect thoſe that appeared and acted in the ſervice) doe
herewith hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſent to your Excellency, the annexed Repreſentation of
our deſires, which we humbly beſeech your Excellency to recommend or
repreſent in our behalfe unto the Parliament, and your Petitioners ſhall
ever honour and pray for your Excellency, &amp;c.</p>
                        <q> 
                           <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                              <body>
                                 <div type="representation">
                                    <head>The humble Repreſentation of the deſires of
the Officers and Soldiers of the Army, under the command of his Excellency Sir
<hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> preſented firſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>o his Excellency, to be by him
preſented to the Parliament.</head>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>1. Whereas the neceſſity and exigency of
the warre hath put us upon many actions, which the law would not warrant, nor
we have acted in a time of ſetled peace, we humbly deſire that before our
disbanding, a full and ſufficient proviſion may be made by Ordinance of
Parliament, to which the royall affent may be deſired)<note n="*" place="margin">In this we deſire no more then the City and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have
done before us, notwithſtanding their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notable and home De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations
againſt the King</note> for our indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and ſecurity in all ſuch
caſes.</item>
                                       <item>2. That Auditors and Commiſſioners may be
ſpeedily appointed and authorized to repaire to the Head quarters of this
Army, to audite and ſtate our accompts, as well for our former ſervice, as
for our ſervice in this Army, and that before the disbanding of the Army,
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction may be given to the Petitioners for their Arrears; that for the
charge trouble and loſſe of time, which we muſt otherwiſe
neceſſarily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe in attendance for obtaining of them, may be
prevented, we having had experience that many have been reduced to miſerable
extremity, even<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114264:27"/>almoſt ſtarved for want of reliefe, by
their tedious attendance, and that no Officer may be charged with any thing in
his accompts, that doth not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly concerne himſelfe.</item>
                                       <item>3. That thoſe who have voluntarily ſerved
the Parliament in the late war, may not hereafter be compelled by preſſe or
otherwiſe, to ſerve as Soldiers out of this Kingdome, nor thoſe who have
ſerved as Horſe-men, may be compelled by preſſe, to ſerve on foot in
any future caſe.</item>
                                       <item>4. That ſuch in this Army, as have loſt
their lives, and the wives and children of ſuch as have been ſlaine in the
ſervice, and ſuch Officers and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as have ſuſtained loſſes.
or have been preiudiced in their eſtates, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering unto the Parliament,
or in their perſons, by ſickneſſe or impriſoment under the Enemy, may
have ſuch allowance, and ſatisfaction, as may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to iuſtice
and equity.</item>
                                       <item>5. That till the Army be disbanded as
aforeſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome courſe may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the ſupply thereof with
money, whereby we may be inabled to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our quarters, that ſo we may
not for neceſſaries be forced to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to the parliaments Enemies,
burthenſome to their friends, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive to the Country, whoſe
preſervation we have alwayes indeavoured, and in whoſe happineſſe we
ſhall ſtill reioyce.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </div>
                              </body>
                           </floatingText>
                        </q>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Courteou-Reader,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The foregoing is a true copy of the Petition promoting in the
Army, which the Parliament are too much offended with, and therefore let the
righteous God and all ingenious men iudge, if the deſires of this Army be not
rationall, iuſt and equitable, and let the Lord of Heaven and Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
what here is deſired, to occaſion ſuch a Declaration againſt this
inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any the
Officers thereof, as is here unto annexed, and let men that love
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>edome and hate tyrants, looke
about and conſider if it be not the deug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe few men that abuſe the Parliament, maliciouſly
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king odious reports <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the
Houſe of the actions of that Army, in the worſe ſence they can deviſe,
as <hi>Stapleton, Hollis, Luke,</hi> and <hi>Earle,</hi> lately did in the like
c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abominable act of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting
Ma. <hi>Tulidah</hi> without ever he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay
for himſelfe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niurie ſo much
former<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y complained of by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>act of the higheſt iniuſtice
in the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aring, and when both his friends
and himſelfe did moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e might be brought to their barie,
that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tly informed of the demeanor of
theſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat
Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or <hi>Tulidah</hi> ſhould
diſcover them at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>emies to the legall and iuſt
liberties of the <pb n="54" facs="tcp:114264:28"/>people, (which to prevent) they became the
only inſtruments to get him his liberty, and with ut hearing they forthwith
got him releaſed.</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <head>A Declaration of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in
Parliament. 
<date>Die Martis, 30. Martii. 1647.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>THat the two Houſes of Parliament having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
information<note n="*" place="margin">The informers are ſaid to be Col.
<hi>Roſſiter,</hi> and Col. <hi>Harlow,</hi> both members of the Houſe of
Commons, and the Army likewiſe.</note> of a dangerous Petition, with
repreſentations annexed, tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ng
to put the Army in a diſtemper and muteny, to put conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the
Parliament, and obſtruct the reliefe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which hath been
contrived and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome perſons in the Army. They doe declare their
high diſlike of that Petition, their approbation and eſteem of their good
Service, who firſt diſcovered it and of all ſuch Officers and Soldiers as
have refuſed to joyne in it, and that for ſuch as have been abuſed, and
by the parſwaſion of others drawn to ſubſcribe it; if they ſhall for
the future manifeſt their diſlike of what they have done, by forbearing to
proceed any further in it, it ſhall not be looked upon as any cauſ to take
away the remembrance &amp; ſence the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have of the good ſervice
they have formerly done, but they ſhall ſtill be retained in their good
opinion, and ſhall be cared for with the reſt of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in all things
neceſſary and fitting for the ſatisfaction of perſons that have done
ſo good and faithfull ſervice, and as may be expected from a Parliament,
ſo carefull to performe all things appertaining to honour and juſtice; as
on the other ſide it is declared, that all thoſe who ſhall continue in
their diſtempered condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and goe on in advancing and promoting, that
petition ſhall be looked upon and proceeded againſt as enemies to the
State, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſturbers of the
publique peace.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Martis 30. Martii.
1647.</date>
                           </dateline> Ordered by the Lords aſſembled in parliament, that
this Declaration be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with printed and publiſhed. 
<signed>
                              <hi>John Brown Cler.
Parliamentorum.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now Sir to conclude the tyrannicall houſe of Lords having moſt
illegal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, barbarouſly, tirannically, and unjuſtly committed me to
priſon, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenced me, under wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe tyranny you are willing to ſuffer me to periſh and then by
your and their whifling, and buking Curs to beſpatter and reproach me in
print, thereby ſtrongly indeavouring to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke me as odiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the
eyes of the ſons of men, as <hi>Job</hi> was in all his botches, and
alaſſe pocre I, muſt<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114264:28"/>be kept in pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> without pen or inke,
acceſſe of friends or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
and ſo deprived of all means to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate my
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ce write in my owne behalfe, and
ſet my name to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing alwayes ready to owne and
iuſtifie my lines, and to ſeale then with my
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> blood, yet my wife muſt be
made a priſoner, and fetched up to your arbitrary Committees for
diſperſing of my bookes, and the book women in <hi>Weſtminſter
Hall</hi> that ſell them, muſt have then ſhops and houſes ſearched
and rob'd of all my bookes, by your Catch poules, and if you ſuſpect any
for printing of them, they muſt be ſure to be dealt worſe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h then if they were Traytors and
enemies to their Country, and have their houſes rob'd, and ſpoyled of their
goods and preſſes, with which they earne bread for them and their families
and carried away by force, before any legall tryall, or conviction of any
crime, contrary to the lawes of the land, <hi>which poſſitively declares,
that no free man of England forfeits his lands, goods or livelyhoods, tell he
be convicted of a crime.</hi> 1 <hi>R.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Cookes</hi> 2. <hi>part
inſtitutes, chap</hi> 103. <hi>fol.</hi> 228. 229. <hi>See the Petition of
Right,</hi> yea and their bodies impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned moſt tyrannicall and
illegally, without baile or maineprize, although there be no collour in law for
the pretended cauſe of their commitment, nor no power in law for any
Committee of your houſe to commit a printer, or any other free man in
<hi>England</hi> to priſon. See the law authorities <hi>mentioned in Judge
Jenkins late printed papers.</hi> And when the priſoner according to the law
of the Kingdome ſues for a <hi>Habias Corpus,</hi> which legally cannot be
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to any priſoner whatſoever, and by vertue thereof be brought before
the preſent Judges of the Kings bench, Juſtice <hi>Bacon,</hi> and
Juſtice <hi>Rowles</hi> yet contrary to law and their owne oathes (which
oaths are before mentioned) they refuſe to deliver the priſoner ſo
uniuſtly impriſoned, or to take baile for his forthcomming, but returne him
back to priſon againe, there contrary to law and iuſtice to be kept without
bail or maineprize. Oh horrible tyrannie oppreſſion, and iniuſtice, and
yet as I am certainly informed, this was the caſe of <hi>Mr. Thomas
Paine</hi> a Printer the laſt tearme.</p>
            <p>Nay your Catchpoules by their owne power, can and have forceably
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and felloniouſly and illegally carried away my proper and truly
com'd by goods to a large value, for which though I complained to your
Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, yet could I not obtaine from their hands one dram of Juſtice,
<hi>See my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination before them, called the reſolved mans reſolution,
pag.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Nay, this is not all for when your members and the Lords and their
catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poules creatures, have ſufficient railed at me, and reproached me, and
tyed up my hands; by depriving me of all meanes (as they thought) to publiſh
any thing for my owne defence, then they as I conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve ioyne together, and git 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114264:29"/>ſome lying Presbyter aſſemblie man or other, (for the
Author concealing his name, and I not able to find it out, I apprehend, and
iuſtly conceive I have iuſt cauſe to lay it to them, it being ſo
ſutable to the conſtant meanes, they and their Creatures, uſe to ſet up
their new reformed Kingdome) to frame, contrive and publiſh to the view of
the world, <hi>a Recantation in my name (that J my ſelfe, though my name be
to it, had not the leaſt finger in, or</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of) thereby to render
me odious to the purpoſe, and to declare me a weather cock fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and as
faſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, and eaſie in changing
my former avowed juſt principles, as the Lords and Commons, and aſſembly
men at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> are, to change theirs; But Sir, if God permit,
I ſhall take a more fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
oppertunity to anotomize that groſſe peice of Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>mentary,
aſſembly knavery. And therefore I muſt plainly tell you, ſeeing the
Lords and Commons at <hi>Weſtm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> have dealt ſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arb rouſly and illegally with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as they have done, 
<note n="*" place="margin">And not with me, but alſo with M.
<hi>Over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on</hi> his wife and
brother, and Mr. <hi>Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> man and maid, who are all yet in perſon,
and can have nor obtain any iuſtice from either of your houſes.</note>and
are worſe then the unrighteous Iudge, that upon no importunity will doe me
Juſtice, I am now in good ſober reſolved earneſt, determined to appeale
to the whole Kingdome and Army againſt them, and it may be thereby come
quittance with them, and meaſure unto them as they have meaſured to me, and
doubt not but to make it evident, that though ſome of your members call the
Army Rebells and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, for conteſting with thoſe that gave them their
power and authority; that they themſelves a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reall Rebells and Traitors, to the truſt repoſed, in them by
the free people of <hi>England,</hi> their Empero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, Lords, and Maſters. And that the Army are really
and truly a company of Rogues, Knaves, and traiterous Villains to themſelves
and their native Country, if they ſhould disband upon any tearmes in the
world, till they have brought them to examplary Juſtice, and made them vomit
up the vaſt ſums of the publiques money, that they have ſwallowed down
into their devowring canniball mawes, and firmly
ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the peace and iuſtice
of the Kingdome, which that they
may faithfully and cordially doe is and ſhall be the daily prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>him that
hath been and will be againe, your true friend if you will repent of your
remiſseneſſe and
ſlackneſſe, and manifeſt your ſelfe to be more firme, active, and
valourous for the good of your Country, <hi>Iohn Lilburn.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>From my uniuſt Captivitie in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi>
for the (viſably almoſt deſtroyed) <hi>Lawes and Liberties of
England,</hi> which condition I
more highly prize though in miſery enough outwardly, then the viſibleſt
condition of any mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber whatſoever, that ſits in either or both houſes,
being all and every of them, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently, palpably and tranſendently
forſworne, having all of them taken Oaths upon Oathes, to mainetaine the
lawes, liberties and freedome of the land and yet in their dayly practice
overthrow and deſtroy them, of which ſin and wickedneſſe, they are all
of them guilty, in regard you all ſit there in ſilence, and doe not
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely and avowedly to the whole Kingdome according to your duty, manfully
proteſt againſt, and declare
your diſlike of their crooked, uniuſt and Englands deſtroying wayes, 
<date>this 31. of <hi>May</hi> 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Lilburne.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114264:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
